<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse of tempting Christ by John Shower.</title>
            <author>Shower, John, 1657-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 112 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60130</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3662</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28141</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10410139</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10410139</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45005</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60130)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45005)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1389:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse of tempting Christ by John Shower.</title>
                  <author>Shower, John, 1657-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>xii, 105 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.D. for John Lawrence,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Divinity.</term>
               <term>Christian life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45005:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45005:1"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE OF TEMPTING CHRIST.</p>
            <p>By JOHN SHOWER.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. D.</hi> for <hi>John Lawrence,</hi> at the Angel in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:45005:2"/>
            <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:45005:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>I Shall not need to urge the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of aſſerting the Divinity of our Bleſſed Saviour, from every Scripture-Medium, that will prove, or illuſtrate it, to argue the firſt part of this Diſcourſe to be ſeaſonable, ſo far as this Text may be improv'd to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it. And the the many ways of Tempting God (particularly with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to his <hi>Providence</hi>) which are afterwards mention'd, may help the Conviction and Recovery of ſome who are guilty, and prevent the Sin of others in the like kind.</p>
            <p>What I preach'd on this Subject, (at a Time when many in this City needed it) againſt <hi>laying great Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers upon the future Determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Divine Providence, (as to the Succeſs of Fleets and Armies abroad,</hi> &amp;c.) it offended ſome who had
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:45005:3"/>been drawn into the Snare, and it may be got Money by it; while others, having ſmarted for their Raſhneſs and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, thank'd me for the Warning, and promiſed to take it, wiſhing they had done it ſooner.</p>
            <p>To the Inſtances of Tempting God, as to his <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Providence,</hi> may be added the falſe and lying Wonders, which the Jews were addicted to. Their Rabbins, and their <hi>Talmud</hi> mention ſtrange Stories of this kind. They had frequent <hi>Exorciſms</hi> by Invocation of the God of <hi>Jacob.</hi> They had <hi>Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets,</hi> and <hi>Ligatures,</hi> and confident Aſſertions, that God gave Power to his Law, his Name, and Attributes, when thus
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Lightfoot</hi> Hor. Heb. in Mat. 24. Vol. 2. p. 243.</note> applied by them, to heal Diſeaſes, and work Signs and Wonders, becauſe their Law was of Divine Original.</p>
            <p>A Deſcription of a <hi>Charmer (Chober)</hi> among the Jews is thus given by
<note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Maimonides</hi> de Idolat. c. 11. §. 10, 12.</note> 
               <hi>Maimonides.</hi>
               <q>He is a Charmer who ſpeaks words of a
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:45005:3"/>ſtrange Language, and without Senſe, and in Fooliſhneſs thinks that theſe words are profitable: That if one ſay ſo or ſo to a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent or a Scorpion, it cannot hurt a Man; and he that ſaith ſo or ſo unto a Man, he cannot be hurt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He that whiſpereth over a Wound, or readeth a Verſe out of the Bible; likewiſe he that readeth over an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant, that it may not be frighted, or that lays the Book of the Law, or the Philacteries upon a Child that it may ſleep; ſuch are not only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Enchanters or Charmers, but of thoſe that generally deny the Law of God, becauſe they make the words of the Scripture, Medicine for the <hi>Body,</hi> whereas they are not, but for the <hi>Soul,</hi> as it is written, <hi>Prov. 3.22. They ſhall be Life unto thy Soul.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Many ſtrange and undoubted In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances may be given of Evil Spirits exorciſed and diſpoſſeſt, by the Invoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the God of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi>
               <pb n="vi" facs="tcp:45005:4"/>and <hi>Jacob,</hi> even by <hi>Pagans,</hi> as well as by <hi>Jews;</hi> or by <hi>Chriſtians</hi> mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Name of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> that many who did not own the Faith, either of <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> yet atteſted upon their own Experience <note n="*" place="bottom">See many Authors cited by Dr. <hi>Whitby,</hi> in his Excellent Diſcourſe <hi>of the Certainty of the Chriſtian Faith in general,</hi> &amp;c. 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1671. Annot. on Ch. 1. §. 3.</note> the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of thoſe Names. It would yet be a Tempting of God, for us to uſe thoſe Names, and expect the like Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, becauſe without a Warrant.</p>
            <p>As to what is ſaid of Tempting <hi>Providence,</hi> by uſing unlawful or ſuſpected Methods to accompliſh our Deſires, and by raſh Appeals to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to decide in doubtful Caſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I might add <note n="†" place="bottom">P. Molinaei <hi>Vates,</hi> lib. 3. c. 21, 22, 23. de Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicio per ſingulare Certamen, quae vulgaris Purgatio in Jure Canonico appellatur. De Purgatione per Aquam ferventem, aut prunas, aut ferrum candens, &amp; per Aquam frigidam, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> many more Examples, particularly concerning <hi>Waters of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation:</hi>
               <q>
                  <note n="‖" place="bottom">Dr. <hi>Whitby,</hi> Ib. chap. 1. §. 5.</note> Waters which had Virtue to diſcover and chaſtiſe the Sinner,
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:45005:4"/>whilſt they cleared the Innocent; as Heathen Writers affirm of <hi>Olachas,</hi> and other Rivers, which were wont to put off their Natures, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Fire to the guilty Perſon; of the <hi>Crateres Palichorum,</hi> and the Sardinian Fountains, which did ſtrike the Thief, or perjured Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, blind or dead; of the Indian <hi>Brachmans</hi> probatory Waters, and many others of that kind. And as the Jews ſay, with much better ground, of thoſe of <hi>Jealouſy,</hi> which being uſed according to the Preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of their Law, to try the Chaſtity of any Woman, of whom her Husband ſhould be jealous, did cauſe the guilty Thigh to rot, and had no like Effect upon the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent; I ſay with <hi>better ground,</hi> for had they failed upon Trial, the Jews could not have own'd that Law for Sacred, which left them ſuch a ſtanding Lie.</q> But for us to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect God's Deciſion of Right and Wrong, of Innocence or Guilt, by ſuch
<pb n="viii" facs="tcp:45005:5"/>like Methods, would be to Tempt him.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only add a Paſſage out of a late. <note n="*" place="bottom">Mr. <hi>Freke</hi>'s ſelect Eſſays, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. of <hi>Divination</hi> and <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> p. 23, 24.</note> Author to the purpoſe of <hi>the tenth Section.</hi>
               <q>What ſhall I ſay of our common Croſſes and Charms? The Devil fights with us like <hi>a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian</hi> flying; pretends himſelf to be vanquiſh'd by us, that he may the better conquer us, through Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by his Flight? So what ſhall I ſay to your other ſet Forms of Words, the <hi>Sieve</hi> and <hi>Sheers,</hi> and ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Trifles and Gewgaws? If Words do any thing really, it muſt be through Faith; and if Faith be once ſo powerful, it can eaſily effect without a ſet Form like Conjuring; but if Words prove powerful without Faith, <hi>latet Anguis in Herba,</hi> we have all the reaſon in the World to apprehend ſome Deluſion from our common Enemy the Devil.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="ix" facs="tcp:45005:5"/>
            <p>There is one thing, which may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducible to this Head of <hi>Tempting Chriſt,</hi> which may be objected againſt ſome Paſſages in a little Book I lately printed, <hi>viz. Some Account of the Holy Life and Death of Mr.</hi> Gea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that they may encourage People, under Trouble of Mind, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, that by opening the Bible, the firſt place they look into, ſhould by Divine Direction be ſuitable for their Support and Relief; or it may add to their Affliction and Melancholy, if they do not ſucceed in ſuch an Attempt, as others have done. 'Tis true, I there relate only Matter of Fact, as I found it written, without intimating that I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove or diſapprove of ſuch a Practice. But leſt any ſhould take occaſion to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the like, and be troubled if they do not; I muſt freely acknowledg, that I know of no ground we have, in that way to look for preſent ſuitable Counſel, or Conſolation. The Holy Spirit is not limited, and may ſometimes direct, and guide an humble doubting Chriſtian.
<pb n="x" facs="tcp:45005:6"/>But 'tis more adviſable to conſider, and enquire what Promiſes and Examples of Holy Scripture, are moſt adapted to your Caſe, and proper for your Support.</p>
            <p>To open the Book, and expect that the firſt Chapter, and Verſe you caſt your Eyes on, ſhould juſt anſwer your Caſe, and adminiſter Reſolution or Comfort, is without ſufficient Ground or War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and is a kind of <hi>limiting</hi> God, and ſo a <hi>Tempting</hi> of him. For what reaſon hath any Man to believe, that God will certainly diſcover, and reveal himſelf that way, to fatisfy his Doubts?</p>
            <p>May a Divine Bleſſing accompany this ſerious Admonition and Warning, to take heed how we Tempt God, by any of the various Methods here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. S.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi>
                  <date>March <hi>the 8th, 169¾</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb n="xi" facs="tcp:45005:6"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Sect. 1. <hi>THE Introduction, Context, and propoſed Method of the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Diſcourſe.</hi> page 1.</item>
               <item>Sect. 2. <hi>Of the Perſon tempted, and ſinn'd againſt by the Jews,</hi> Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>His Exiſtence before his Incarnation prov'd againſt the</hi> Socinians. p. 5.</item>
               <item>Sect. 3. <hi>What was the particular Sin of the Jews, in the Wilderneſs, here called a Tempting of Chriſt.</hi> p. 12.</item>
               <item>Sect. 4. <hi>Of the Puniſhment by Fiery Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents. The Wiſdom of Providence therein. Of the Serpent in Paradiſe. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon what Accounts Serpents have been reckon'd Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred and Venerable by the Heathens.</hi> p. 16.</item>
               <item>Sect. 5. <hi>How we may be guilty of the like Sin, Explicitly and Directly, or Implicitly. Two Inſtances of the former.</hi> p. 25.</item>
               <item>Sect. 6. <hi>The many ways of implicit, indirect Tempting Chriſt. Some Inſtances with reſpect to his</hi> Truth. p. 36.</item>
               <item>Sect. 7. <hi>Of Tempting God, and Chriſt, with reſpect to the</hi> Divine Power, <hi>in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Inſtances.</hi> p. 41.</item>
               <pb n="xii" facs="tcp:45005:7"/>
               <item>Sect. 8. <hi>Of Tempting Chriſt, with reſpect to his</hi> Knowledg. p. 50.</item>
               <item>Sect. 9. <hi>Of Tempting God, and Chriſt with reſpect to his</hi> Providence, <hi>in ſeveral Inſtances.</hi> p. 53.</item>
               <item>Sect. 10. <hi>It is a Tempting of</hi> Providence, <hi>to uſe unlawful, or ſuſpected Means to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh our Deſires, or ſupply our Wants.</hi> p. 62.</item>
               <item>Sect. 11. <hi>Of laying Wagers concerning the future Determinations of Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</hi> p. 67.</item>
               <item>Sect. 12. <hi>Of Tempting Chriſt with reſpect to his</hi> Inward Grace, <hi>and the Aſſiſtance of the Holy Spirit: Eſpecially by bold ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turing upon Temptation, and the Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Sin.</hi> p. 70.</item>
               <item>Sect. 13. <hi>Of Tempting God and Chriſt, as to his</hi> Patience. p. 85.</item>
               <item>Sect. 14. <hi>The Improvement of this Diſcourſe, for Conviction of Sin, and Humiliation. The Aggravations of this Tempting Chriſt. The Danger of it, as applied to our Nation, from this Example of the Jews.</hi> p. 87.</item>
               <item>Sect. 15. <hi>An Exhortation to all ſorts of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, inſtead of Tempting Chriſt, to make Trial and Proof of his Goodneſs and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, in a way of Duty, Obedience, and Dependance.</hi> p. 97.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45005:7"/>A DISCOURSE of Tempting Chriſt.</head>
         <epigraph>
            <bibl>
               <hi>1 COR. x. 9.</hi>
            </bibl>
            <q>
               <p>Neither let us tempt Chriſt, as ſome of them alſo Tempted, and were deſtroyed of Serpents.</p>
            </q>
         </epigraph>
         <div n="1" type="section">
            <head>SECT. I. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Introduction, Context, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Method of the following Diſcourſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>WE experience the mighty Force of <hi>Example,</hi> to draw or to diſſwade; when bare Counſel will not move, and naked Precept makes little Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45005:8"/>It is eaſier to oppoſe and contradict the moſt poſitive Rule, to deſpiſe and make light of the plaineſt Prohibition, and Caution againſt Sin, than when we ſee the Evil of it as in a Glaſs, by ſome remarkable Inſtance of Divine Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity. On this Account the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Part of the Holy Scriptures is of excellent Uſe; and accordingly the Examples of God's Antient Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the Jews, are frequently referr'd to in the New Teſtament. They are ſaid to be <hi>Types,</hi> and <hi>Patterns</hi> unto us, to inſtruct us what we may expect, if we imitate their Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, by the Righteous Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of god, that followed them.</p>
            <p>A GOOD part of this Chapter is imployed by the Apoſtle, in admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing and warning theſe <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> againſt ſeveral particular Sins, from the Conſideration of the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments which God inflicted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> for the like. Tho they were his peculiar People, he
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45005:8"/>would not ſpare them, but did ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther execute Vengeance with the greater Severity and Speed. They enjoyed many Advantages above the reſt of the World; eſpecially as <hi>to them belonged the Covenant, and the Adoption:</hi> On which Account they are called <hi>their Fathers,</hi> ver. 1. which the <hi>Jews</hi> could not otherwiſe be to theſe <hi>Corinthians,</hi> who were Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, and ſome of the Firſt-fruits of the Gentile Church. <hi>Types,</hi> and <hi>Examples unto us,</hi> ver. 6. to warn us againſt ſuch and ſuch particular Sins, from what they ſuffered in the Wilderneſs for the like. Adding, that <hi>theſe things are written for our ſakes,</hi> ver. 11. <hi>on whom the Ends of the World are come.</hi> That is, on our account, who live in the latter Ages of the World; when thoſe latter Days are begun, in which the great Change, foretold by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets to be made by the Meſſiah's Kingdom, doth take place; which Kingdom is to laſt, and increaſe to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45005:9"/>the end of the World, without the expectation of any other conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Change of that Nature. It is for our ſakes, on whom the Ends of the World are come, that theſe things are written. That thereby we may know and be convinced, that, whatever the Difference may be imagined between <hi>Chriſtians</hi> and <hi>Jews,</hi> between <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>the Law</hi> and <hi>the Goſpel,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Typical Egypt, Wilderneſs,</hi> and <hi>Canaan</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the <hi>Antitype</hi> to theſe things amongſt us <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> whatever the Difference may be between us and them, and whatever Advantages may lie on our ſide; yet if we will not take warning by <hi>their Example,</hi> we muſt expect the like Severity of Divine Juſtice, as they experienced.</p>
            <p>AMONG other Provocations, of which the Jews were guilty, and which the Apoſtle takes notice of in this Chapter, <hi>This</hi> in theſe words deſerves to be conſidered;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45005:9"/>
               <hi>Neither let us tempt Chriſt, as ſome of them alſo tempted,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I SHALL conſider <hi>the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the Antient Jews,</hi> and what <hi>Sin</hi> that was which is here refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to, and <hi>the Puniſhment</hi> of it. 2. How <hi>We</hi> may be ſaid to <hi>tempt Chriſt;</hi> what is the Nature of <hi>that Sin,</hi> or how many ways we may be guilty of it. 3. Cloſe with a Practical Exhortation, to impreſs and improve the whole.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="section">
            <head>SECT. II. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of the Perſon tempted, and ſinn'd againſt by the Jews,</hi> Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>His Exiſtence before his Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation prov'd againſt the</hi> Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians.</p>
            </argument>
            <p n="1">I. LET us conſider this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>the Jews.</hi> We are cautioned not to tempt Chriſt,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45005:10"/>
               <hi>as They alſo tempted him.</hi> Before I ſpeak to the Nature of their Sin, and the Puniſhment of it, whereof we have a more particular account, <hi>Numb.</hi> 21. it will be neceſſary to enquire <hi>who is the Perſon offended,</hi> how <hi>the Jews</hi> in the <hi>Wilderneſs</hi> can be ſaid to have tempted <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſo long before his Incarnation; which is the Apoſtle's Charge here, and the Ground of his Admonition to us, not to incur the like Guilt.</p>
            <p>THE Socinians, and others who diſown the <hi>Divinity</hi> of our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour,</hi> are here perplexed, to evade the force of the Argument for the Exiſtence of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> before he was born of the <hi>Virgin Mary:</hi> For the Scripture ſpeaks frequently concerning the Jews as <hi>tempting Jehovah,</hi> and of their being pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for it in the Wilderneſs; and it is plain that this Paſſage re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers unto that time, by the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their <hi>being deſtroyed by Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents.</hi> Now it was for <hi>tempting
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45005:10"/>of Chriſt,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, that they were ſo deſtroyed: Therefore Chriſt is <hi>Jehovah,</hi> the true God, and did exiſt before his Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>THERE are <hi>three</hi> things they pretend, whereby to weaken the Force of this Argument. 1. Some of them will have it to be <hi>a Created Angel</hi> who led the Jews in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, and whom they tempted, and ſinned againſt. Others ſay that <hi>Moſes</hi> is to be underſtood by the word <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and that their Sin was in tempting him. A third ſort find fault with <hi>our Tranſlation,</hi> and that this Verſe ought to be read, either thus, Neither tempt ye <hi>God,</hi> as they tempted <hi>him;</hi> or thus, Neither tempt ye <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as they tempted <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. AS to the firſt Evaſion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>a Created Angel:</hi> Not only is there no ſuch Charge againſt them in the Hiſtory, as <hi>tempting
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45005:11"/>of an Angel;</hi> nor is <hi>an Angel</hi> any where ſaid <hi>to be tempted</hi> by the Jews. But the Angel of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant who conducted them in the Wilderneſs, is ſaid to be <hi>Jehovah,</hi> who led them by a Pillar of Cloud by Day, and of Fire by Night, <hi>Exod.</hi> 13.21. compared with <hi>Chap.</hi> 23. <hi>ver.</hi> 21. where he is called <hi>an Angel.</hi> But what is ſaid of him will by no means agree to a created Angel. <hi>Behold I ſend an Angel before thee, to keep thee in the way, and to bring thee into the place which I have prepared. Beware of him, obey his Voice, provoke him not: for he will not pardon your Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">II. WITH as little reaſon is <hi>Moſes</hi> pretended by <hi>Socinus</hi> to be here meant, as the Perſon tempted by the Jews. It is true, they ſpake againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> and ſtrove with him, <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.2, 4. and God was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked by it, as if it had been done
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45005:11"/>againſt himſelf. <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>See Mr.</hi> Daillé <hi>Serm.</hi> in loc. <hi>and</hi> J. Placaei Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſput. 12<hi>m</hi> in loc. 4<hi>to. p.</hi> 130. de Argumentis quibus efficitur Chriſtum prius ſuiſſe quam in utero B. Virginis, &amp;c.</note> But they are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaid <hi>to tempt Moſes.</hi> And he himſelf doth plainly diſtinguiſh their Sin here referred to, from their ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving with him, and ſpeaking againſt him, <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.2. and <hi>ver.</hi> 7. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared. <hi>And</hi> Moſes <hi>ſaid unto them, Why chide ye with me? Wherefore do ye tempt the Lord?</hi> And he called the Name of the place <hi>Maſſah,</hi> and <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribah, becauſe of the chiding of the Children of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and becauſe they tempted the Lord, ſaying, Is the Lord amongſt us?</hi> To pretend therefore that this is the ſenſe, Neither tempt ye Chriſt <hi>as they tempted Moſes,</hi> is neither agreeable to Grammar or Reaſon: For <hi>the ſame Perſon</hi> ſinned againſt by them, we are cautioned not to offend; not to ſin after the like manner, againſt the ſame Object; not to tempt <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as they did.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45005:12"/>The Greek Particle <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, will ſo carry it.</p>
            <p n="3">III. THE other Pretence or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil againſt our Tranſlation, hath as little Strength. There is one Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſcript here in <hi>England,</hi> we are told, wherein this Verſe is thus read, <hi>Neither tempt ye God,</hi> as they tempted <hi>him.</hi> But tho that Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript be pretended to be very an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, there are others of greater Antiquity that read it as we do: And, except one or two of the antient Writers of the Church, who read it <hi>the Lord, Neither tempt ye the Lord,</hi> and explain it ſtill of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> except them, it hath been proved againſt the Socinians that all Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies of this Epiſtle, Manuſcript and Printed, and all the Verſions of the Greek and Latin Fathers, from the end of the ſecond Century until now, do all read it as we do; <hi>Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tempt ye Chriſt, as they alſo tempted him.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:45005:12"/>
            <p>BUT others will ſay it may be read thus, Neither tempt ye <hi>Chriſt</hi> as they tempted <hi>God.</hi> It were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to reply to this, that there is no ſuch word in the Text. But what the Socinians would gain, if we ſhould allow it, I cannot ſee. Neither tempt ye <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as the Jews tempted <hi>God.</hi> Hereby they <hi>equal</hi> at leaſt, if not <hi>prefer Chriſt unto God.</hi> As Chriſtians ſinning againſt Chriſt, anſwers to the Jews ſinning againſt God; ſo <hi>Chriſt</hi> temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Chriſtians, anſwers unto <hi>God</hi> tempted by the Jews: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if the Sin and Puniſhment of the Iſraelites be propoſed as our <hi>Warning,</hi> the Force of the Example is loſt, if it be not an equal Sin, or greater, for us to <hi>tempt Chriſt,</hi> than for the Iſraelites to tempt <hi>God.</hi> And if it be propoſed as <hi>a Type,</hi> the Argument is yet ſtronger, and the Preference is given unto Chriſt. Either way will conclude that he is not a <hi>Creature,</hi> and that he did exiſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45005:13"/>before his Incarnation; otherwiſe theſe Jews in the Wilderneſs could not have ſinned againſt him. And thus for the Perſon ſinned againſt, Neither tempt ye <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as they alſo tempted him.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="section">
            <head>SECT. III. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>What was the particular Sin of the Jews, in the Wilderneſs, here called a Tempting of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p n="2">II. THE particular Sin refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to of the Iſraelites, was their impatient
<note n="*" place="bottom">Numb. 21.4, 5, 6.</note> Murmuring and Diſcontent, their Diſſatisfaction and Complaint, concerning the way which God took to lead them into <hi>Canaan,</hi> and of the Proviſions he made for them in the way, and of the Time and Seaſon of it. For
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45005:13"/>in their March through the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs they had ſome Succeſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> who came out of their own Country to fight againſt them; and thereupon being puft up with their Victory, they ſuppoſed they ſhould as eaſily prevail againſt the <hi>Idumeans,</hi> who refuſed them leave to paſs through their Country. They hoped that with the like Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs againſt them, they might di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly and ſpeedily enter into the promiſed Land. But, inſtead of this ſhort and eaſy way to <hi>Canaan,</hi> God reſolves to ſpare the <hi>Idumeans</hi> at this time, and commands the Iſraelites to compaſs the Land of <hi>Edom,</hi> and take a long Circuit round the Mountains of <hi>Idumea.</hi> Upon this occaſion, we find this People break out into Diſcontent againſt God their Leader, forgetting all the former Wonders of his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Power. And this is that which the Apoſtle calls a tempting of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who as <hi>the Angel of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45005:14"/>Covenant</hi> conducted them in the Wilderneſs. As he calls the Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings and Afflictions which the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites indured in <hi>Egypt, the Reproach of Chriſt;</hi> it being part of the Commendation of <hi>Moſes</hi> by the Apoſtle, and an Inſtance of his <hi>Faith,</hi> that he preferred <hi>the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of Chriſt</hi> before the Treaſures of <hi>Egypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>UPON this, and ſeveral other Occaſions, they complained and murmured; and are therefore ſaid to have <hi>tempted God ten times,</hi> after they had ſeen his <note n="*" place="bottom">Numb. 14.22.</note> Miracles, and had abundant Proof of his Preſence and Care. The Jewiſh Writers do particularly reckon up the ſeveral <hi>ten Temptations;</hi> but whether the exact number of <hi>ten</hi> be intended in the Expreſſion, is very doubtful; it may rather import repeated, mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied Temptations; as when <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> told <hi>Laban,
<note n="†" place="bottom">Gen. 31.41.</note> Thou haſt changed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45005:14"/>my Wages Ten Times;</hi> that is, very frequently.</p>
            <p>THEIR Sin might very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be called <hi>a tempting of him:</hi> For they were not content to go to <hi>Canaaan</hi> in the way which he would have led them, nor were they ſatisfied with the Proviſions that he made for them in the way; but complained of their <hi>Manna,</hi> as light Bread, deſpiſing of it. They would have every thing they had a Mind to, and in that way and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner which they themſelves would chuſe; and thereupon would have put the Power and the Wiſdom, the Truth, and the Goodneſs of God, to farther trial: And by falling of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten into ſuch a Sin, they tempted <hi>his Patience,</hi> to ſee how long he would bear with them. <hi>How often,</hi> ſays the Pſalmiſt, <hi>did they provoke him in the Wilderneſs; and tempt him in the Deſart? Yea, they turned back and tempted God; and limited the Holy One of</hi> Iſrael. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.40, 41.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="section">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:45005:15"/>
            <head>SECT. IV. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of the Puniſhment by Fiery Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents. The Wiſdom of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence therein. Of the Serpent in Paradiſe. Upon what Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts Serpents have been rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon'd Sacred and Venerable by the Heathens.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p n="3">III. IT was for this Sin that they were puniſhed with <hi>Fiery Serpents,</hi> which coſt many of them their Lives. There were many ſuch in that Wilderneſs, who were before reſtrained, but now let looſe: <hi>Serpents,</hi> that by their Venom fired their Blood, and heat their Bodies, ſo as to torment them with Thirſt, and that in a place where there was no Water. We read of the biting of ſome Serpents, that it
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45005:15"/>affects the Patient with Madneſs. By theſe <hi>Fiery Serpents</hi> they were ſtopt in the laſt Year of their Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, before they got into the Land of Promiſe. And on this account they murmured at <hi>Salmonah.</hi> But the Sin that was thus puniſhed, and that of their worſhipping the Golden Calf, is concealed by <hi>Philo the Jew;</hi> and <hi>Joſephus,</hi> out of more Love to his Country-men, than Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity to Hiſtory, doth not take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it.</p>
            <p>'TIS the Conjecture of the Learned <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Tenniſon <hi>of Idolatry,</hi> c. 14. p. 352, &amp;c.</note> Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> that
<q>the <hi>Seraphim</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim</hi> were Images, or Symbols of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring Angels in the form of <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery, Flying Serpents;</hi> as <hi>Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bim</hi> were ſuch Images with the Faces of <hi>Oxen.</hi> So the word <hi>Saraph</hi> is uſed, <hi>Numb.</hi> 21.6, 8. <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.15. In <hi>Egypt, Arabia,</hi> and <hi>Lybia,</hi> and <note n="†" place="bottom">Herodot. l. 2. Cic. de Nat. Deor. l. 1.</note> other places,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45005:16"/>there were flying fiery Serpents. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> mentions ſuch Creatures, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.29. And <note n="*" place="bottom">Vid. <hi>G. Moebium</hi> de Aeneo Serpente, Exercit. 2. c. 2. §. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Abarbanel</hi> ſaith of ſuch flying Serpents, that they were Reddiſh, after the Colour of Braſs: If that were their natural Colour, great Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition might be made to it by the ſwift Motion of their Wings, and the Vibration of their Tails in the bright Atmoſpheres of <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia</hi> and <hi>Egypt.</hi> And ſo were called <hi>fiery,</hi> not only becauſe of the Heat of their Venom, cauſing extraordinary Inflammations and Thirſts in the Body bitten by them; but becauſe they appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſuch, when they flew in the Air.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not ſtay to ſhew what a vile, what a painful, what an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſual Plague, and (as to ordinary means) an incurable one, this of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45005:16"/>
               <hi>the Fiery Serpents</hi> was; which gave occaſion to the Erection of <hi>the Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen Serpent,</hi> as a Figure of <hi>the Meſſiah</hi> to be lifted up upon the Croſs. But if we refuſe to look to him and believe on him, if we do not receive healing Virtue and Influence from him; the more dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Puniſhment which we may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, and the ſorer Vengeance that we are to look for, is what this Plague of <hi>Fiery Serpents</hi> did but ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pify and repreſent. For the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of theſe Jews, is but an Emblem of a more fearful and fiery Indignation, againſt thoſe who will not take warning, but <hi>tempt Chriſt,</hi> as ſome of them alſo did, and were deſtroyed in the Wilderneſs.</p>
            <p>IT ſeems an excellent Inſtance of the Wiſdom of the Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, to order this Puniſhment of the Iſraelites by <hi>Serpents,</hi> and to make way thereby for a Cure by looking to <hi>the Brazen Serpent.</hi> This was proper to rivet the ſenſe of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:45005:17"/>firſt Evil done to Mankind by the Devil, when <hi>the Serpent beguiled our firſt Parents in Paradiſe;</hi> and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve or recover the Memory of it; which we have no more reaſon to take to be all <hi>Allegory,</hi> than the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing part of the Moſaick Hiſtory, concerning the Iſraelites March in the Wilderneſs, and their Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment here by Fiery Serpents.</p>
            <p>THE famous <hi>Origen,</hi> ſays St. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom,</hi> turned Paradiſe ſo into an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legory, that he took away the Truth of the Story; and not only turned <hi>Adam</hi> out of the Garden, but the Garden out of Paradiſe.</p>
            <p>IT might withal be of uſe to rectify the Error of ſome of the Jews, derived from the Heathen Idolaters, <hi>of the Gods appearing in the form of Serpents:</hi> For we read of the
<note n="*" place="bottom">See more <hi>Bochurti</hi> Opera, vol. 1. de Serpente Tentatore, <hi>p.</hi> 842.</note> 
               <hi>Babylonians,</hi> that they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped <hi>a great Dragon,</hi> a Creature
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45005:17"/>of a Serpentine Kind: and that in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and in <hi>Phoenicia,</hi> they ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed unto <hi>Dragons,</hi> and called them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>their good Genius's. Eſculapius,</hi> the God of the Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, was worſhipped under the ſame Form: A <hi>Dragon</hi> is uſually annex'd to his Statue. The ſuperſtitious <hi>Romans</hi> placed the Head of <hi>a Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon</hi> at the Entrance into their Houſes, imagining thereby to conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liate the Favour of the Gods. And <hi>Alexander the Great</hi> is repreſented as begotten by <hi>a Serpent</hi> with his Mother. The like is feigned of the Birth of other Great Men amongſt the Gentiles.</p>
            <q>
               <p>IN the earlieſt Ages (ſaith Dr. <hi>Tenniſon</hi>) and inhabited Countries of the World, the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures on Earth principally reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced were <hi>Oxen</hi> and <hi>Serpents.</hi> Serpents were lately worſhipped in <hi>America,</hi> as appears from <hi>Aco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta,</hi> and others. And of old they were ſacred in <hi>Egypt.</hi> We ſee no
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:45005:18"/>Table of <hi>Iſis,</hi> or <hi>Oſiris,</hi> or <hi>Bacchu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> without a Serpent. Among how many other Nations, it hath been accounted ſacred, may <note n="*" place="bottom">Citing <hi>Pignorius</hi> de Mensâ Iſiacâ, <hi>p.</hi> 23, 24.</note> there b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> read at large. The Reaſons why Serpents were thus honoured might be, partly becauſe they could twine themſelves into all Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures; becauſe of the mighty E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nergy of their Venom, and becauſe of their mighty Bulk, and becauſe they live to a great Age, are of quick and piercing Sight, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new their Youth by putting off their Skin: Laſtly, by reaſon that the Heathen were over-powered by the Craft, Malice and Pride of <hi>the Devil,</hi> who deluded Man in that Shape, and would as it were redeem the Loſs he ſuſtain'd in the Curſe of that Creature, by tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it into a venerable Idol.</p>
               <p>If the <hi>Seraphim</hi> (or good An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels miniſtring in the World)
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:45005:18"/>had not appeared in ſome ſuch Form, <note n="*" place="bottom">Dr. <hi>Tenniſon,</hi> Ib. <hi>p.</hi> 245.</note> it would be difficult to give an account of the Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> by a Dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in the ſhape of a Serpent. That Serpent is ridiculouſly pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the form of a creeping one before the Fall: It is impoſſible to conceive our firſt Parents ſo ſtupid, as to have entred into a Dialogue with ſuch a Creature, without any Aſtoniſhment. But being uſed to the <hi>Shecinah</hi> of the <hi>Logos,</hi> and to the Appearance of miniſtring Angels, ſhewing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in ſome ſuch winged form, it is eaſy to conceive, upon that Suppoſition, how they might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain ſome familiar Diſcourſe with a Creature aſſuming that Image in a very ſpendid and glorious manner. The Text aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures us the Form is now changed by God's Curſe, moſt probably
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:45005:19"/>from that of a ſplendid fiery <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raph,</hi> to that of a mean creeping Serpent, not moving aloft in the Air, but licking the Duſt. And a part of the Puniſhment of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> may confirm this. For it is ſaid, God guarded Paradiſe againſt them by a Cherub and a Flaming Sword, which was eſteem'd by the Jews a ſecond Angel; and may be aptly ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd a <hi>Saraph,</hi> or flaming Angel, in the form of a fiery flying Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, whoſe Body vibrated in the Air with Luſtre, and may be fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſcribed by the Image of ſuch a Sword. <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith, that the <hi>Serpent from the beginning was one that ſacrilegiouſly uſurped the Divine Image.</hi> This ſoundeth as if the Devil in Serpentine-Form had repreſented part of the <hi>Shecinah</hi> of the <hi>Logos,</hi> and that <hi>Eve</hi> conceived him to have been an Angel appertaining to his glorious Preſence, and a Miniſter
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:45005:19"/>of his Pleaſure; and was come forth from him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>NOW the Puniſhment of the Jews by theſe <hi>fiery flying</hi> Serpents, may be a means to revive the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of the <hi>Paradiſical Serpent,</hi> and to prevent or cure ſuch Fancies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, of <hi>their Divinity,</hi> as the Heathens entertain'd.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="section">
            <head>SECT. V. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>How we may be guilty of the like Sin, Explicitly and Directly, or Implicitly. Two Inſtances of the former.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>BUT I proceed from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of <hi>their Sin,</hi> and <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> to enquire into the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Kinds of <hi>our Tempting Chriſt,</hi> how far we may now be guilty: That <hi>we</hi> may not tempt <hi>Chriſt</hi> as <hi>They</hi> did. And conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:45005:20"/>that all Power and Authority is committed unto him, that the Government of the World is upon his Shoulders, that the Father hath committed all Judgment unto the Son, that the Adminiſtration of the Kingdom of God in this World, is in the Hands of <hi>Chriſt</hi> the Mediator; every undue and unneceſſary Trial which we make of the <hi>Truth,</hi> or <hi>Power,</hi> or <hi>Knowledg,</hi> or <hi>Grace,</hi> or or <hi>Providence,</hi> or <hi>Patience</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> is a Tempting of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> unto whom we are related as <hi>our Lord and King,</hi> under whoſe immediate Government we all are, and by owning of our Chriſtianity avow our ſelves to be. Therefore every tempting of God is a tempting of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> And by reaſon of our clearer Knowledg of the Meſſiah, and our Chriſtian Profeſſion, we may be guilty of a more criminal tempting of Chriſt than ever the Jews were, and with many higher Aggravations.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:45005:20"/>
            <p>IN general, to tempt God or Chriſt, is to make <hi>a needleſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due Trial,</hi> or <hi>Inquiry</hi> concerning his Attributes, or his Will; what God doth know, or can do, or will do. And this may be either <hi>implicitly,</hi> as the Language of our Hearts and Lives; or by a more <hi>direct</hi> and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit</hi> Tempting of him. The <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> is more common: but let me name two ſpecial Inſtances of <hi>the Latter.</hi> As,</p>
            <p n="1">I. WHEN we demand an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary Diſcovery of the Divine Power, to confirm and prove that which is ſufficiently proved already. This is <hi>a direct explicit tempting of God</hi> and Chriſt. Tho God had given the <hi>Jews</hi> ſufficient Evidence of his Power, in the various Miracles which he wrought for them in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and in the aſtoniſhing man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>their Deliverance</hi> out of it, and afterwards at <hi>the Red Sea,</hi> and in <hi>the Wilderneſs;</hi> yet we have
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:45005:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>frequent Inſtances of their Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief and Murmur, doubting of the Divine Power upon every Occaſion. <note n="*" place="bottom">Pſal. 78.17, <hi>to</hi> v. 20.</note> 
               <hi>Can he furniſh a Table in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs? Can he give Bread alſo, and provide Fleſh?</hi> Tho he gave <hi>Manna</hi> in the Morning, and <hi>Quails</hi> in the Evening, and their Bread was mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly rained down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; yet they queſtioned whether he can give <hi>Water</hi> too. And ſome of the Jews tell us, the <hi>Manna</hi> had the virtue to quench <hi>the Thirſt,</hi> as well as to ſatisfy <hi>Hunger.</hi> And tho God had condeſcended, twice to give them Water out of a Rock, as at <hi>Rephidim,</hi> and at <hi>Horeb;</hi> yet do they demand another Proof of his Power and Preſence, <hi>viz. a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble furniſhed with Fleſh.</hi> This was a direct tempting of God.</p>
            <p>THUS the Scribes and Phariſees, after our Saviour had ſufficiently proved his Divine Commiſſion by
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:45005:21"/>many undeniable <hi>Miracles,</hi> they would have him do ſome new Feat for their ſakes. <note n="*" place="bottom">Mat. 8.11. &amp; 16.1.</note> 
               <hi>Maſter,</hi> ſay they, <hi>we would fain ſee a ſign from Heaven.</hi> They would try whether he could do ſuch things, as the Prophet <hi>Elias</hi> did. They had ſcarce wiped their Eyes, ſince they ſaw a Sign and a Miracle, ſufficient to convince them; but that is not enough, they would ſee another; as if he had not wrought any before. To the like purpoſe they ſpeak when he was <hi>upon the Croſs,</hi> if he would <hi>then</hi> come down; that is, if he would give them <hi>a Miracle in their own way,</hi> and of their own chuſing, then they would believe.</p>
            <p>IT is well known, that <hi>the Ceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Miracles</hi> is one pretence of <hi>Infidelity</hi> in our Age, tho a very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable one. Not to mention the late Account of
<note n="†" place="bottom">Viz. <hi>The Cure of the French Girl, and of Mrs.</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage.</note> ſome Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:45005:22"/>of Providence that are matter of Diſcourſe amongſt us <hi>at preſent,</hi> (as what is next to <hi>Miracle</hi> at leaſt; for I leave theſe things to be further conſidered, enquired into, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected upon, by thoſe that have Opportunity, and Capacity for it.) The Pretence is unreaſonable, not to believe the Scripture for want of <hi>more Miracles,</hi> when the New Teſtament, and the Divine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Chriſt, has been already confirmed by many and ſufficient Signs and Wonders. It is therefore a Tempting of God, to demand a further Diſcovery of his Almighty Power, in this, and in every Age, to confirm that which was proved by Miracles in former Ages. And that the ſame Doctrine of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel was atteſted by Miracles for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, we have as great Aſſurance, as the Nature of the thing is capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of: And he is very unreaſonable who will deſire more Evidence, or not be ſatisfied with that. But our
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:45005:22"/>Lord has told us, that, with moſt Men that make this Objection, it is meer Cavil: For <hi>if they will not believe</hi> Moſes <hi>and the Prophets.</hi> And we may add upon the like ground, <hi>If they will not believe Chriſt and his Apoſtles,</hi> after the Evidence of ſo many Miracles; <hi>neither would they believe, tho one ſhould riſe from the dead.</hi> (The Miraole, of all others, which theſe Men are moſt like to pitch upon, if they might have their Choice.) No, nor if all the Miracles mentioned in the Goſpel were done before their Eyes.</p>
            <p n="2">II. IT is <hi>a direct Tempting of God, and Chriſt,</hi> to demand ſome Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Divine Manifeſtation, to atteſt his Kindneſs, and prove his Preſence, when he has ſufficiently done it already. When, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Promiſes that God hath made, and the Experience that we and others have had of his Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to them; we muſt have ſome
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:45005:23"/>Extraordinary Sign of his Love and Favour to encourage us, or we will not believe. The Jews in the Wilderneſs are charged with this, <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.7. And the place was called <hi>Maſſah, Temptation,</hi> as a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial of it: as it was alſo called <hi>Meribah,</hi> upon the account of their childing, ſtriving, and contending there. They queſtioned whether God was among them, unleſs he would do thus and thus, as they deſired. After all the Proof which they had of his Preſence, they would not believe it without far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Teſtimony, and Evidence in their own way. Now to doubt and disbelieve the Divine Favour and Preſence, after ſuch peculiar Experience, and Atteſtation as he had given them, is plainly to <hi>Tempt</hi> him. <hi>They believed not God,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>and truſted not in his Salvation. Tho he had commanded the Clouds from above, and opened the Doors of Heaven. They ſinned ſtill,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:45005:23"/>and believed not for his wonderous Works. They turned back, and temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted God, and limited the Holy One of</hi> Iſrael. <hi>They remembered not his Hand, nor the Day when he delivered them from the Enemy.</hi> Pſal. 78.22, 32, 41, 42.</p>
            <p>AFTER this manner, the Devil tempted Chriſt to throw himſelf down from the Pinacle of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; <note n="*" place="bottom">Matth. 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>If thou be the Son of God.</hi> To which our Saviour replies, <hi>It is written, Thou ſhalt not tempt the Lord thy God.</hi> That is,
<q>I am ſufficiently ſatisfied that God is my Father, I do not queſtion his Care over me, I am ſatisfied of his gracious Preſence with me, I need no ſuch new Trial of his Kindneſs and Love.</q>
            </p>
            <p>IF at any time we are ingaged in any ſpecial Work and Duty, and meet with Oppoſition therein; but have the Promiſe of God to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:45005:24"/>us to go on, and have the Experience of his former Goodneſs and Power in difficult Caſes, as thoſe Jews had: For us to diſtruſt God, without farther and new Signs of his Favour, is directly to <hi>Tempt</hi> him. The Iſraelites fell often into this Fault: tho they had ſeen his Works of Power, as in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding of the Sea; ſome Works of Majeſty and Terror, as in the Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Lightning, Fire, Smoke and Earthquake, at the giving of the Law; ſome of his Severity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Sin, as in drowning of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> in the Puniſhment of <hi>Korah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram;</hi> and the Plagues that befel themſelves; and had alſo Experience of many Works of Favour, Kindneſs and Grace, and of a watchful Providence for their conſtant Protection and Supply, Guidance and Conduct; and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by had the higheſt Security that God would accompliſh his Promiſes to them: They yet queſtioned
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:45005:24"/>and doubted after all. They ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times profeſſed their Faith and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in God, upon ſome new Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance or ſome mighty Work of Providence for their ſakes. Upon ſuch an Occaſion we read that <hi>the People feared the Lord, and believed the Lord, and his Servant</hi> Moſes, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.31. But upon the next difficult Trial, they forgat the Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Heaven, they renounced their own Experience, they deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Faithfulneſs of God, which before they acknowledged, and are again guilty of Murmuring and Unbelief.</p>
            <p>THIS kind of tempting of God many amongſt us may be guilty of: when, after eminent Preſervations in a time of Danger, or wonderful Deliverances from threatning Death, or other peculiar Favours of Divine Providence, we will not thereby be led to Repentance and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to Truſt and Dependance; but overlook all that God has done
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:45005:25"/>for us, as if it were nothing, unleſs he will do ſomewhat more. As if all his former Works had nothing in them of Value, or Obligation, or Encouragement. Which leads me to conſider the next thing.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="section">
            <head>SECT. VI. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>The many ways of implicit, indirect Tempting Chriſt. Some Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with reſpect to his</hi> Truth.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly.</hi> THERE is an <hi>Impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit, Indirect Tempting of God;</hi> as to his <hi>Truth, Power, Knowledg, Providence, Grace, Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> &amp;c. whereof we may be many ways guilty.</p>
            <p n="1">I. AS to <hi>the</hi> Truth <hi>of God.</hi> When we disbelieve what he hath <hi>promiſed</hi> or <hi>threatned,</hi> and queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Fidelity to make it good.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:45005:25"/>This is contrary to the Nature and Office of <hi>Faith,</hi> whoſe Excellency it is to give Glory to God, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving in the moſt difficult Caſes. Many a convinced Sinner, under the ſenſe of his former Guilt, when he ſees the Aggravations of his Folly, and of his Rebellion, does thus tempt God, by doubting of the Truth of his Word to pardon and forgive ſuch Sinners as he, tho he ſhould never ſo truly and unfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly Repent Whereas God has expreſly told us, that <hi>if the Wicked forſake his Way, and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteous Man his Thoughts, he will multiply Pardons:</hi> And that <hi>the Blood of Chriſt cleanſeth from all Sin.</hi> Many a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, timerous Chriſtian, under the ſenſe of their own Weakneſs, may likewiſe incur this Guilt, by queſtioning the Grace of God to enable them to perſevere, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the preſent Temptations they meet with, or thoſe they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect: Tho God has told us, that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:45005:26"/>
               <hi>his Grace ſhall be ſufficient,</hi> and that <hi>he will not ſuffer us to be tempted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove what we are able;</hi> and that <hi>he who hath begun a good Work, will carry it on, and perfect it to the Day of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>GOD had expreſly promiſed to bring the <hi>Jews</hi> into the Land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> but their Journey had been long and tedious, they were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged becauſe of the Way, they were founder'd in their Patience, and could not ſtay God's Leiſure; and therefore queſtioned his Word of Promiſe; and ſo they tempted him concerning his <hi>Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BUT it is more common to tempt him with reſpect to the Truth of his <hi>Threatnings.</hi> As if he were not reſolved to fulfil his Word againſt thoſe who are finally Impenitent, and Unbelieving. Tho he hath told us, That <hi>he that made them will will ſhew them no Mercy:</hi> And that <hi>the Wicked ſhall be turned into Hell, with All of every Nation that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:45005:26"/>to forget God:</hi> And that <hi>Chriſt ſhall be revealed from Heaven in fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Fire, to render Vengeance to them that know not God, and obey not the Goſpel:</hi> Yet Sinners believe it not, they will venture to ſee what will become of the Threatning: By a like Preſumption with thoſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Let him make haſte, and haſten his Work, that we may ſee it: Let the Counſel of the Holy One of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and his threatned Vengeance draw nigh and come, that we may know it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE firſt Impoſture, by which the Devil tempted and allured our firſt Parents, was of this kind; <hi>Ye ſhall not ſurely die.</hi> As if the threatning of Divine Wrath againſt obſtinate and incorrigible Sinners, had more of <hi>Terror</hi> in it, than of <hi>Truth;</hi> and that Men ſhould never be called to an Account hereafter, for what they do in this World: at leaſt ſhould never be condemned to Eternal Torments, tho they live
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:45005:27"/>and die in their Unbelief, and Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitence. As if God would be more merciful than his Threatnings can import, tho he hath told us, how far his Mercy ſhall reach, and to whom, and that the Day of his Patience is concluded at fartheſt with the Day of our Death. But thus to <hi>preſume</hi> againſt expreſs Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that there ſhall be <hi>no Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and <hi>no Hell,</hi> or that it ſhall not be <hi>Eternal,</hi> when it is as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſaid that <hi>the Wicked ſhall go away into Everlaſting Puniſhment, as the Righteous into Life Eternal;</hi> this is to Tempt God with reſpect to his <hi>Truth.</hi> Men in the Vigor of their Strength, when their Spirits are inflamed with Wine, and their Hearts hardened by Atheiſtical Company and Diſcourſe, may dare to talk thus preſumptuouſly; but we find the ſame Perſons on a ſick Bed, when they approach to the other World, and apprehend they can ſtay no longer in this, have
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:45005:27"/>commonly other Apprehenſions of theſe things: their Hearts ſink, their Courage fails them, and they would rather <hi>die the Death of the Righteous,</hi> however they formerly derided the Folly of <hi>their Life.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="section">
            <head>SECT. VII. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of Tempting God, and Chriſt, with reſpect to the</hi> Divine Power, <hi>in ſeveral Inſtances.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p n="2">II. AS to <hi>the Power of God,</hi> we may be ſaid to Tempt him <hi>two</hi> ways. 1. When we que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion the Sufficiency of his Power to make good his Word. 2. When we limit and confine it, to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed and diſcovered in our own way and manner.</p>
            <p n="1">1. WHEN we queſtion <hi>the Power of God</hi> to accompliſh his Word, by reaſon of ſome Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:45005:28"/>that are in the way. In this reſpect the <hi>Jews</hi> tempted God, after he had promiſed to bring them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Canaan:</hi> When the Spies, who returned from viewing the Land, and gave them an account of <hi>the Giants</hi> and <hi>the Sons of Anak</hi> that were there, and the ſeeming Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility <note n="*" place="bottom">Numb. 14.</note> of conquering it; they were quite diſheartened. Thus, ſays our Saviour, did <hi>the Sadduces err</hi> about the Poſſibility of <note n="†" place="bottom">Mat. 22.29.</note> 
               <hi>the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the Body, not knowing the Scripture, nor the Power of God.</hi> But we have very ſtrange Thoughts of Almighty Power, if we do not believe, and grant that it can do much more than we are able to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend diſtinctly, after what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner it can be done.</p>
            <p n="2">2. WHEN we <hi>limit</hi> and <hi>confine</hi> the Power of God, as to the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and ſeaſon of its Manifeſtation. The Jews are charged with this
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:45005:28"/>Tempting God, and <hi>limiting the Holy One of</hi> Iſrael. At one time the <hi>Manna</hi> doth not pleaſe them, they muſt have <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and then they muſt have <hi>Water:</hi> They muſt have what they had a Mind to, and in their own Method, or they queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whether God could do this or that. To this purpoſe do many diſtruſt God, when he doth not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer their Prayers, and grant their Deſires, at <hi>that time,</hi> or in <hi>that way,</hi> when they expect it: They will wait on the Lord no longer, if he do not deliver and ſave them, either by ſuch Inſtruments, or in ſuch a Method, as they have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived and carved for themſelves.</p>
            <p>MANY Inſtances might be named of <hi>a ſinful limiting the Power of God.</hi> One, among others, is that of <hi>raſh Appeals to Heaven,</hi> expecting that God by his powerful Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſhould interpoſe to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion of doubtful Caſes. And this Men do, in the uſe of ſuch things,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:45005:29"/>unto which ſome notable Effects are aſcribed, which they were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver inabled or appointed, by Nature or Divine Inſtitution, to produce: As when a Perſon was indicted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Suſpicion, or for a Fault that was ſecretly committed, or upon the Teſtimony but of one Witneſs, he was to purge himſelf by <hi>Ordeal Fire</hi> or <hi>Water;</hi> that is, to put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upon God, and Appeal to him.</p>
            <p>THIS was allowed by ſome of the Laws of <hi>Charles the Great,</hi> and was in frequent uſe in this Nation in the <hi>Saxons</hi> time. Many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in the <hi>ninth</hi> and <hi>tenth Century</hi> may be given of this, as a common Practice in the Chriſtian World: when there was not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Evidence of a Man's Guilt, to put him on ſuch Extraordinary Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, expecting ſome miraculous Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of God, to vindicate his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence, or conclude againſt it. In ſuch doubtful Caſes they ſaid they would go <hi>ad Judicium Dei,</hi> they
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:45005:29"/>would appeal to Heaven. Many ways they had of this, in different Forms, and ſeveral Ceremonies, and particular Prayers, with Faſting and Adjurations in the Name of God, to the particular Element; various according to the Quality of the Perſon, whether <hi>a Freeman,</hi> or <hi>a Slave;</hi> that is, one of a mean and baſe Condition; the <hi>former</hi> was to be tried by <note n="*" place="bottom">See <hi>Spelman</hi>'s Gloſſary, <hi>p.</hi> 435, 436. <hi>N. Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con</hi>'s Hiſtory of the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> firſt Part, <hi>p.</hi> 55, 56. <hi>Dugdale</hi>'s Origines Judiciales, <hi>p.</hi> 86, 87. <hi>Coke</hi>'s 9 Repl. 32. <hi>Glanvil.</hi> p. 114.</note> 
               <hi>Fire,</hi> and the <hi>latter</hi> by <hi>Water,</hi> hot or cold.</p>
            <p>BUT what Ground have we to think, that if Men are <hi>Innocent,</hi> the Power of God will this way preſerve them; or if they be <hi>Guilty,</hi> that he will leave them to ſuffer by it? It is true, he appointed under the Law a Draught of bitter Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters for <hi>the Woman ſuſpected of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery,</hi> to diſcover her Innocency, or Guilt; this was peculiarly enacted
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:45005:30"/>by God himſelf, who doubtleſs would aſſiſt ſuch Extraordinary Procedure, as was of his own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution. But it is not for us to uſe ſuch Methods of our own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing, and expect the like Succeſs.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">Lib. 8. Chap. 19.</note> 
               <hi>PHILIP de Comines</hi> tells us of two <hi>Franciſcan Friars</hi> at <hi>Florence,</hi> who offer'd themſelves to the Fire to prove <hi>Savonarola</hi> to be a Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick: But a certain <hi>Jacobine</hi> offer'd himſelf to the Fire, to prove that <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vonarola</hi> had true Revelations, and was no Heretick. In the mean time <hi>Savonarola</hi> preach'd, and made no ſuch confident Offer: nor durſt he venture at that new kind of Fire Ordeal. But if all four had paſt through the Fire, and died in the Flames, what would that have proved? Had he been an Heretick, or no Heretick, the more or the leſs for the Confidence of two or three Zealots?</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:45005:30"/>
            <p>THEY who are well eſtabliſhed in the Belief of the future Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, will be eaſily ſatisfied, that we ought not to expect that God ſhould oblige himſelf to declare one way or other in ſuch Caſes.</p>
            <p>IT is not unlikely that the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of <hi>Duelling</hi> came in upon this bottom; for the Trials by <hi>ſingle Combat and Battel,</hi> are founded on the like Superſtition, and Folly of People, thus appealing to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, to decide Caſes in an Extraordinary Manner.</p>
            <p>IT has formerly been frequent among the <note n="*" place="bottom">See Sir <hi>Will. Temple</hi>'s Miſcellanies, Part 2. Eſſay 3. Sect. 4. <hi>p.</hi> 243.</note> Northern Nations, when the Right of Titles, or of Lands was difficult, thus by <hi>legal, ſingle Combats,</hi> to decide it: Or when a Perſon accuſed, did abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely deny what the Accuſer affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and no other Proof on either ſide could be produced. And even
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:45005:31"/>after the Profeſſion of Chriſtianity, among the <hi>Goths,</hi> and thoſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms erected by them, this Practice continued. But upon the farther Progreſs of Learning and Civility, when this could be no longer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved; it made way for
<note n="*" place="bottom">See Biſhop <hi>Hall,</hi> Epiſt. 2. Dec. 4. <hi>Of the bloody <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of ſingle Combats: The Danger and Sinfulneſs thereof.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>private Duels,</hi> and for <hi>the Lie</hi> being a juſt Ground of fighting in Point of Honour, becauſe it had been ſo in Point of Law, during the barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Ages. But it were ſhameful it ſhould be ſo eſteemed amongſt us Chriſtians. The Example of <hi>Charles the Fifth,</hi> and <hi>Francis the Firſt</hi> of <hi>France</hi> gave it much Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and much of the beſt Blood in <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> has been ſpilt after this manner, eſpecially in <hi>France,</hi> during ſeveral Reigns, till by the juſt Severity of <hi>the preſent French King</hi> (how unjuſt ſoever in other things) this Cuſtom is in great meaſure extinguiſhed there.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:45005:31"/>
            <p>SOME have expected the like Succeſs, upon receiving <hi>the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lord's Supper.</hi> Among ſome of the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> if any thing were ſtolen in a Monaſtery, where one of the Houſe muſt have been the Thief, and all denied it; they were all to receive <hi>the Sacrament,</hi> and theſe words were pronounced, <hi>Corpus Domini noſtri ſit tibi ad Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bationem,</hi> Let the Body of our Lord be thy Trial. There are many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who will take <hi>the Sacrament</hi> upon their Aſſeveration of ſuch or ſuch a thing, to aſcertain the Truth of it; as if what they had ſaid, or ſworn, muſt needs be true, in caſe no evil Effect did viſibly follow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their taking the Sacrament. But <hi>theſe,</hi> and <hi>other ſuch <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes</hi> of that Divine Inſtitution, are a bold Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of God. It is deſigned and appointed, to commemorate the Death of Chriſt till he come, not to diſcover <hi>Thieves</hi> or <hi>Liars;</hi> nor to attain <hi>other Civil Ends,</hi> for which
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:45005:32"/>it hath been formerly uſed, and is yet required in ſome parts of the World.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="section">
            <head>SECT. VIII. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of Tempting Chriſt, with reſpect to his</hi> Knowledg.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly.</hi> THERE is Another Inſtance of Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting God and Chriſt, <hi>viz. with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to his Knowledg.</hi> And this we may be guilty of ſeveral ways. Partly by adventuring to ſin <hi>in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret,</hi> when we are concealed from the Knowledg and Notice of our Fellow-Creatures. We do in effect ſay,
<q>Can he behold me when the Door is ſhut? Can his Eye pierce the thick Cloud?</q> Thus we tempt him as to his <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg,</hi> and <hi>Omniſcience,</hi> whether he can diſcern us, and make our Sin
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:45005:32"/>to find us out. Partly by pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ask Counſel of God, when we are reſolved already in our own Minds what to do. After Vows, to make Inquiry, and after being reſolved to ask Advice, is a Mockery and an Affront, and <hi>a Tempting of God,</hi> as if he did not know the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes of our Heart.</p>
            <p>BUT there is a more plain Tempting of him in reſpect of <hi>his Knowledg,</hi> by <hi>Hypocriſy</hi> in Divine Worſhip: by drawing nigh to him with our Bodies in the Solemnities of Religion: by appearing in a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping Poſture before him, and taking his Name within our Lips, while our Hearts are not ingaged. Hereby <hi>we Tempt God,</hi> and would make a bold Trial whether he can diſtinguiſh between Subſtance and Shadow, Reality and Appearance, between the Worſhip of the Heart, and the Complement of the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Man, between a dead Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſs and a living Sacrifice.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:45005:33"/>
            <p>IN ſhort, we Tempt God as to his <hi>Knowledg,</hi> by the ſecret Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of any Wickedneſs, under the Pretence and Profeſſion of Religion. This Charge is given againſt the Wife of <hi>Ananias, Acts</hi> 5.9. that <hi>ſhe tempted God, and lied unto the Holy Ghost;</hi> becauſe ſhe and her Husband kept back <hi>part of the Price of their Poſſeſſion,</hi> when they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to bring <hi>the whole:</hi> And ſo diſcovered a covetous Mind, and the prevailing Love of this World; while they kept up the Profeſſion of Religion, and would maintain the Reputation of being zealous, and forward Diſciples. Every <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite,</hi> who does compaſs God about with Lies, and lives in the Allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of any ſecret Luſt, under the colour of Religion, does thus <hi>Tempt</hi> God, and Chriſt as to his <hi>Knowledg.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="section">
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:45005:33"/>
            <head>SECT. IX. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of Tempting God, and Chriſt with reſpect to his</hi> Providence, <hi>in ſeveral Inſtances.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly.</hi> ANOTHER Inſtance of a criminal Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of God, is with reſpect to <hi>his Providence.</hi> All Power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity being now in the Hands of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> we may tempt him in this Particular, either,</p>
            <p n="1">1. BY diſtruſting his Care, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and Aſſiſtance, when we have ſufficient Ground for our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance, and Confidence that he will not fail us. While we keep in the way of our Duty, he has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to be with us, and never to forſake us. Now tho the ordinary way of Relief for the preſent be not in view, it is to tempt God, <hi>to
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:45005:34"/>diſtruſt him;</hi> as if our Hope were periſhed, and he had forgotten us. It is true, in ſome Caſes we may not poſitively conclude either way, but ſay with <hi>David, Let the Lord do what ſeemeth him good:</hi> But in others, we ſhould truſt him for the particular Mercy, when all Means ſeem to fail in an ordinary way: As when Mercies are expreſly, and particularly promiſed, as a Son was to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the Kingdom un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>David.</hi> The like when God leads us into Straits by ingaging us in his Service; as when <hi>Iſrael</hi> followed him in <hi>the Wilderneſs,</hi> in order to the Poſſeſſion of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Land. When they had no Water to drink, nor Food to eat, and ſo no poſſibility of Supply in the Wilderneſs, they ought poſitive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to have expected Supplies from God, in an extraordinary way: And it is reckoned as their Sin, that they did <hi>not believe.</hi> Thus when <hi>Chriſt</hi> was led by the Spirit into the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:45005:34"/>and there was no Bread there to ſatisfy his Hunger, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſes to work a Miracle for his Supply, and leans upon an Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Providence <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Gilpin</hi> of Satan's Temptatious, Part 3. c. 11.</note>.</p>
            <p>MOREOVER, when the things we want are common and univerſal Bleſſings, and ſuch without which we cannot ſubſiſt. Such Supplies from Providence we muſt poſitively expect, tho we ſee not the way, whence they ſhould ariſe to us: becauſe God is ingaged to preſerve his Creatures in their ſeveral Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to clothe the Graſs of the Field, and to feed the Birds of the Air, <hi>&amp;c. <note n="†" place="bottom">Mat. 6.30.</note> Shall He not much more clothe you, O ye of little Faith?</hi> Hence the Prophet <hi>Habakkuk</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves upon a rejoicing Confidence in God, when neither Field, nor Tree, nor Flock could yield any Relief in an ordinary way. The
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:45005:35"/>like may be ſaid, when God is emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently ingaged for our Help, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his Honour lies at ſtake in that very matter; ſo that whether he <hi>will help</hi> or no, or whether he <hi>is able,</hi> is become <hi>the Controverſy,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which Religion in its Truth, or the Honour of God, is to be tried. In ſuch a Caſe, we are ingaged to a certain Belief of Help. The three Children upon this Ground, did not only aſſert that God <hi>was able</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver them, but that <hi>he would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver</hi> them, that the Fire ſhould not burn them. On the like Ground <hi>Chriſt</hi> rebukes his Diſciples for Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief, in their Fears of Shipwrack in a great Storm, becauſe <hi>he was with them;</hi> and conſequently it had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidably contradicted his Deſign, and reflected upon his Honour, if he had ſuffered his Diſciples at that time to be drowned. But,</p>
            <p n="2">2. WE Tempt him as to <hi>his Providence,</hi> if we pretend to truſt it, and yet neglect the common and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:45005:35"/>ordinary Means, which he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and may be had. Thus the Devil would have <hi>Chriſt</hi> to caſt himſelf down from the Pinacle of the Temple, when there was an eaſy way of going down ſafely by the Stairs and Steps. We may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect God's Bleſſing upon our Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, in the uſe of lawful Means, but muſt not pretend to truſt him with the neglect of what is in our Power to be done. We muſt not look that Water ſhould be fetched out of a Rock for us <hi>by Miracle,</hi> when there is hope we may find a Spring, if we will but dig for it; or that we ſhould be able to ſwim croſs an Arm of the Sea, when we may have a Veſſel to tranſport us. We muſt not look for Bread from Heaven, as the Iſraelites had it, if the Ground will bear Corn, and we will not plough or ſow. It is to Tempt God, to expect Recovery from Sickneſs, without the uſe of Means, when they may be had;
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:45005:36"/>or Supplies of Poverty, without Diligence to ſeek Relief; or Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance in Danger, if we ſit ſtill and will do nothing that is within our reach. When our Lord was <hi>in the Wilderneſs,</hi> and Proviſion could not be had for the Multitude that followed him; he then made uſe of his Almighty Power to multiply a few Loaves, and two or three little Fiſhes, into ſufficient Proviſions for thouſands: But at other times, when he was near a Town, we find that <hi>he ſent his Diſciples to buy Food,</hi> Joh. 4. To expect the End, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out uſing the Means that are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our Power, is <hi>a Tempting of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BUT it is more common in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Religious Matters, than in Civil and Temporal Ones. How many do hope for Divine Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, without fearing God, and working Righteouſneſs; and that they ſhall die the Death of the Righteous, tho they continue all
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:45005:36"/>their Days to be Workers of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity?</p>
            <p n="3">3. WHEN we repine, and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur at his Diſpoſal of us and ours. When we are diſſatisfied with our State and Condition in the World; when the Station he has put us in, and the Proviſion he has made for us, doth not content and pleaſe us; tho it may be we have ſuch Fruits of his Wiſdom, Care and Love, as to theſe things, that many of our Betters have not. Herein did the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſin in the Wilderneſs: This Diſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction occaſioned all their Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings, and Complaints; upon the account whereof they are ſo often ſaid to <hi>Tempt God,</hi> and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. IT is a tempting of God as to <hi>his Providence,</hi> when we venture upon <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nneceſſary, Avoidable Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> and expect that God ſhould interpoſe to preſerve us. He that will give his Angels charge to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve us, <hi>while we keep in his way,</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:45005:37"/>hath not promiſed to bring us off in Safety when we expoſe our ſelves to Danger, without his Warrant. Thus <hi>our Lord</hi> replies to <hi>Satan,</hi> that it is to <hi>Tempt God</hi> for any one to fall from the Pinacle of the Temple, upon a falſe Aſſurance, that the Angels would be at hand to prevent his Danger.</p>
            <p>MANY have paid dear for their Preſumption in this reſpect, and too late bethought themſelves, Where was my Call? What did I here? What a raſh Adventure did I make? St. <hi>Paul</hi> would not have had the Centurion put to Sea in ſtormy Weather; and it coſt them the loſs of all that they had, but their Lives, that they did not hearken to him: ſo much was God diſpleaſed with ſuch bold adventurous Enterprizes. <hi>A wiſe Man feareth, and departeth from evil,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>but a Fool rageth and is confident:</hi> Prov. 14.16. When <hi>David</hi> had raſhly ſent three of his Captains, to fetch him Water
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:45005:37"/>from the Well of <hi>Bethlehem</hi> by the Gate, with the extreme hazard of their Lives; as ſoon as he reflects, his Heart ſmote him, and he would not drink it, ſaying,
<note n="*" place="bottom">2 Sam. 23.17.</note> 
               <hi>Is not this the Blood of the Men, that went in Jeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardy of their Lives?</hi> God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <hi>the Leper</hi> ſhould dwell alone without the Camp, and that no clean Perſon ſhould come near him, becauſe of the Contagion. They who are <hi>in Health,</hi> are not obliged to accompany with <hi>the Sick</hi> in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectious Diſeaſes, unleſs to give them neceſſary Succour in a Spiritual or Temporal Way, and therein we may expect Divine Preſervation.</p>
            <p>IT is obſervable, that, when the Plague was great in <hi>Iſrael, David</hi> would not go up to offer Sacrifice at <hi>Gibeon,</hi> where was the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of the Lord that <hi>Moſes</hi> had made in the Wilderneſs, and the Altar of Burnt-Offering, becauſe <hi>he
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:45005:38"/>was afraid of the Sword of the Angel of the Lord,</hi> that is, <hi>of the Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> 1 Chron. 21.30. And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> tho he deſired to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt; yet when his Life was ſought after, he fled away from his Enemies, becauſe he would not Tempt the Providence of God.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="section">
            <head>SECT. X. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is a Tempting of</hi> Providence, <hi>to uſe unlawful, or ſuſpected Means to accompliſh our Deſires, or ſupply our Wants.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly.</hi> IT is another Inſtance of Tempting God as to his <hi>Providence,</hi> when we make uſe of unlawful or ſuſpected Methods to accompliſh that which we deſire. Many ſick People, by reaſon of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:45005:38"/>under Pain, from the Fear of Death, or over-eager Deſires of a ſpeedy Recovery, will venture to make uſe of ſuch things in order to it, as have no natural Virtue or Influence towards ſuch an Effect: As the pronouncing of ſuch or ſuch hard words, to charm away the Diſeaſe, the carrying ſuch or ſuch things about them, uſing <hi>Taliſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Figures,</hi> &amp;c. and many other ſuch Methods, whereof no tolerable Account can be given, but that the Effect, when there is any, muſt proceed from a very ill Cauſe, or what we have reaſon to ſuſpect to be ſo.</p>
            <p>I could mention Inſtances of ſad Effects of uſing ſuch Methods of Cure: Among others there is one <note n="*" place="bottom">By my Reſpected Friend Mr. <hi>J M,</hi> Letters to a ſick Friend, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>, <hi>Letter</hi> 15.</note> printed, of a Gentlewoman ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving an Ague, a Beggar gave her a Charm to hang about her Neck,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:45005:39"/>bid her not read it, but when ſhe was cured, burn it. The Miniſter of the Pariſh (being a ſober, learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and pious Conformable Divine) came caſually to viſit her: She tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him the Medicine, and the Cure which had attended it, threw it into the Fire in his Preſence; but he catching it, read it; the words were, <hi>Ague, farewel, till you and I meet in Hell.</hi> Upon hearing of which ſhe fell into her Ague again, with greater Violence than ever; and alſo into a deep Melancholy, which occaſion'd her to lay <hi>violent Hands on her ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE like may be ſaid for <hi>Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets,</hi> and things uſed to preſerve from Infection in a time of <hi>Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> or for Security of Mens Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in a time of War; or of Herbs and Plants to preſerve from Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crafts, and Power of Evil Spirits. Such things, I mean, which can have no natural Efficacy to produce the deſired Effect; as <hi>Charms,</hi> and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:45005:39"/>
               <hi>Spells,</hi> and <hi>Magical Arts,</hi> and many inſignificant Forms of Words, with their ſeveral Modes and Manners of Pronunciation, uſed to avert Evils from themſelves, or their Subſtance, their Fruits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which many, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the
<note n="*" place="bottom">See Dr. <hi>Towerſon</hi> on the Firſt Commandment, Part 8. And Mr. <hi>Incr. Mather</hi>'s Eſſay for recording of <hi>Illuſtrious Providences,</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Chap. 8. p. 248, 254. and 264, 284. at large.</note> 
               <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly make uſe of, with great ſhew of Devotion.</p>
            <p>THESE things are granted by all to have no natural Aptitude for theſe Effects; and therefore muſt receive their Force, either from <hi>God,</hi> or from <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſer,</hi> or from <hi>the Devil.</hi> Not from God, for there is no Divine Revelation on which to bottom ſuch a Faith, which the Apoſtles had in the Miracles they wrought. If we expect it, either from our Selves, or from the Devil; it is to give the Glory that is due to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:45005:40"/>God, either to <hi>Satan,</hi> or to <hi>our Selves</hi> When we uſe any ſuch Means with the expectation of Succeſs, it is a kind of Magick which the Devil himſelf owns, and gives Life to: So is i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to uſe any Arts, Rites, or Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, not underſtood, of which we can give no Rational or Divine Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count: Tho he may not be viſibly and corporally preſent, or require preſently any farther Covenants from the Uſers of them.</p>
            <p>THE Devil, no queſtion, is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at his own Rites and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, tho Men diſcern him not; and may, upon the uſe of them, ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly produce thoſe Effects, which may gain Credit to them. They fence themſelves, as one ſaith, with the Devil's Shield, againſt the Devil's Sword: Tho the Perſons have no Intention of making Application to the Devil; yet if they make uſe of ſuch Means for their Preſervation from Diſeaſes or Dangers, or for the attaining of other Purpoſes,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:45005:40"/>they are chargeable with this Guilt, becauſe the Succeſs cannot reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be expected from any other, but <hi>Satan.</hi> Eſpecially if we will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in ſuch a Practice, after the expreſs Cautions given by God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the uſe of ſuch things, and his Deteſtation of them, declared by caſting out the <note n="*" place="bottom">Levit. 19. &amp; 20.6, 23. &amp; Deut. 18.10, 11, 12.</note> Nations that poſſeſſed the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Iſraelites, upon this very Account.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="section">
            <head>SECT. XI. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of laying Wagers concerning the future Determinations of Divine Providence.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly.</hi> IMIGHT under this Head, add a modern Inſtance of <hi>Tempting the Providence of God,</hi> or that which I think <hi>is a
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:45005:41"/>very bold Trifling with it;</hi> for Men to lay conſiderable <hi>Wagers,</hi> and make a Trade of it likewiſe, upon the future Determinations of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, about the Succeſs of Fleets, and Armies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whether ſuch or ſuch a beſieged Town ſhall be taken, and delivered up upon ſuch a Day or no. I would fain ask what Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection there is from the Word of God, or what Example of holy Men in Scripture, or in former Ages, to countenance this Practice. What Encouragement have Men to pray for the Bleſſingof Heaven eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Morning, upon ſuch new Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of getting Money? If you pray for Succeſs in theſe Wagers, you muſt ſometimes contradict ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part of your own Prayers, for the Progreſs of the Reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the Welfare of <hi>England;</hi> and if you wage one with another, God cannot hear one of you, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out denying the other, who lays on the other ſide. If Men loſe an
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:45005:41"/>Eſtate, or bring themſelves and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies to Poverty or Straits, by ſuch Methods as theſe; they will be apt to have many uneaſy Thoughts about it, and hardly will be able to ſay with <hi>Job, It was the Lord who gave, and who hath taken away, Bleſſed be his Holy Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BESIDES that, it argues ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the Temper of Mens Minds, that is worſe than the thing it ſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> the want of a due Concern a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Publick Affairs of <hi>Europe,</hi> and of what God is doing in the World. But it not only diſcovers an ill Temper of Mind, but has a very great Influence to make it worſe. As has been obſerved of ſeveral who have fallen into this new way of Trade.</p>
            <p>SOME ſuch Reflections, it may be, would reach unto other doubtful ways of <hi>Trade</hi> in this City. But I pretend not to underſtand Matters of Trade ſufficiently, ſo as to give a poſitive Opinion in theſe Affairs;
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:45005:42"/>but earneſtly deſire you would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, and conſider this, That, <hi>in doubtful Caſes, the ſafeſt ſide is to be choſen.</hi> And thus for Tempting God as to his <hi>External Providence.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="section">
            <head>SECT. XII. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of Tempting Chriſt, with reſpect to his</hi> Inward Grace, <hi>and the Aſſiſtance of the Holy Spirit: Eſpecially by bold venturing upon Temptation, and the Occaſions of Sin.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly.</hi> ANOTHER way of Tempting God, and Chriſt, is with reſpect to <hi>his inward Grace and Aſſiſtance.</hi> Either,</p>
            <p n="1">1. WHEN we are not ſatisfied with the ordinary Influence of the Spirit of Grace, in the Duties of Religion; but are diſquieted and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:45005:42"/>perplexed, if we have not ſuch <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Tranſports,</hi> and <hi>Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances,</hi> and <hi>Manifeſtations</hi> of ſpecial Kindneſs, as he hath not promiſed: If we have not ſuch ſenſible Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, and Quickning in every Ordinance, ſuch Enlargement in every ſolemn Duty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If we have not theſe, we make hard Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions againſt God and our ſelves: But this is to <hi>preſcribe</hi> to God, and ſo is <hi>a Tempting</hi> of him. The like may be ſaid of thoſe who limit God unto ſuch Means, and unto ſuch a Time, for their Aſſurance and Peace of Conſcience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or elſe they are ready to deſpair of it for ever. It is to oblige God abſolutely, where he has not bound himſelf: what we deſire, not being abſolutely neceſſary in it ſelf, or ſo neceſſary as the Glory of God ſome other way.</p>
            <p>VVE muſt not therefore make Experiments of his Love to us, by his granting our Deſires in theſe Particulars. A Father will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:45005:43"/>a Child to ſay, If you love me, let me have this or that, at ſuch a time, and in ſuch a manner; but when he ſubmiſſively begs and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives it, he may ſay, Now I know my Father loves me. But we Tempt God, when we would tie him up to our Circumſtances, of Time, Manner, and Meaſure, in theſe, as well as in other Caſes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. WHEN we voluntarily run into <hi>Temptation,</hi> and hope the Grace of God will ſecure us; tho we do, or may, very well know, that where we go, and what we do, is like to prove <hi>a Snare,</hi> and an <hi>Occaſion</hi> of Sin. If in the diſcharge of our Duty to God we meet with Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, we may hope his Grace will be ſufficient for us: But if we will play upon the Hole of the Aſp, and come near the Cockatrice Den; if we will walk by the Houſe of the ſtrange Woman, when we may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void it: If we will make bold with the Opportunities, and Incentives,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:45005:43"/>and Provocatives of Sin: If we will frequent ſuch Places, and ſuch Company, as did formerly inſnare us: If we will gratify our Senſes, our Appetites, or our Curioſity in ſuch Things, whereby we and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have formerly been defiled; and then expect <hi>the Extraordinary Aſſiſtance of God's Grace</hi> to preſerve us, this is <hi>a Tempting of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>HE that dares come cloſe to the Threſhold of a Sin, as one ſays, will ſoon be pluck'd within the Door; for he hath Tempted the Lord his God. He that cannot ſwim, and will plunge himſelf into a deep River, if he ſink and be drowned, may thank his own Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption. You know how unable you are to ſtand againſt Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and therefore it is deſperate Boldneſs to adventure where you are ſure to be Tempted. <hi>Can a Man take Fire into his Boſom, and his Clothes not be burnt?</hi> Prov. 26.27. You put your ſelves out of the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:45005:44"/>Protection of God's Grace, and give the Devil an Advantage againſt you; and ſo it is no wonder if you are overcome. You cannot pretend the Strength of the Temptation for your Excuſe, for you might have avoided the Snare. Never ſay that you could not reſiſt the Tempra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it was ſo ſtrong, when you might have avoided it, ſo as not to have been Tempted.</p>
            <p>THE more we know of the Corruption of our Nature, the more Reaſon ſhall we ſee for daily Prayer to God, that he would <hi>not lead us into Temptation:</hi> for we are ſeldom brought into Temptations, and brought off from them, without Sin. When the Devil comes to us, he cannot ſay that he finds nothing in us upon which to faſten: As is ſaid concerning our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour,</hi> Joh. 14.30. <hi>The Prince of this World cometh, and hath nothing in me.</hi> His Temptations could not enter, there was no inward Luſt to receive
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:45005:44"/>them. But our Hearts are ready to kindle upon the leaſt Spark that falls: As ſoon as Satan knocks, we open the Door and entertain him. We have ſo much Experience of this, that it were the greateſt Folly in the World to venture upon Temptation, and expect the Help of that Grace, which we know we have forfeited. A Man may as well put his Finger into the Fire, and hope he ſhall not feel Pain.</p>
            <p>IF <hi>Peter</hi> will go into the High Prieſt's Hall without a Warrant, no wonder if he fall. If People will marry without any regard to Religion in their Choice; if they care not where they dwell, or with whom, or what kind of Perſons they have for their Domeſticks; if Perſons that pretend to Religion will frequent Play-Houſes, and read filthy Hiſtories, or Comedies, or obſcene Poetry, (for the Wit or Language-ſake, as they ſay; that
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:45005:45"/>is, will rake into a filthy Dunghil, in hopes of finding a Jewel, with the manifeſt hazard of being poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned by the Stench;) if they will adventure the corrupting of their Principles, by hearkening to every bold Atheiſt, that will burleſque the Holy Scriptures, and overturn the Foundations of all Chriſtianity, if not of Natural Religion too; ſuch Perſons they <hi>tempt God</hi> to leave them to themſelves; and the Event will prove what need there was of praying, and indeavouring, that we may not fall into <hi>Temptation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I INSIST the longer upon this, becauſe it is ſo neceſſary to be conſidered by All: to take heed how we tempt God, by making bold with the Occcaſions of Sin. It is a merciful Providence to have our Circumſtances, and Condition of Life ſo ordered, that we muſt go out of our way to Sin, we muſt ſeek it with ſome Difficulty. For more Grace is needful to ſave us
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:45005:45"/>from Sin in the Neighbourhood of great Temptations, than while we are at a diſtance. Every one there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, according to the Sins he knows himſelf moſt inclined to, ſhould watch to keep as far as lawfully he may from Temptation. Why ſhould we eat that which we know we muſt vomit up again? do that which we know we muſt Repent of? And if you may not eat, why ſhould you taſte? And if you may not taſte, why ſhould you deſire to See it, or have it before you, or come near it? Read the fifth, ſixth and ninth Chapters of the <hi>Proverbs;</hi> and what is ſpoken concerning one Sin, is true of the Occaſions that lead to others.</p>
            <p>IF we will not keep at a diſtance from the Snare, we gratify Satan, and provoke God to leave us in his Hands. It is poſſible you may come off ſafe from the Occaſions to ſin, but you are not ſure of that Grace that is needful to it. Your
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:45005:46"/>Experience may teach you, your frequent Falls may inſtruct you, how dangerous it is to have Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Objects <hi>near,</hi> and <hi>in view.</hi> To ſee whether I am able to reſiſt Temptation, when I may avoid it, is boldly to tempt God, and to ſin for Trial-ſake. We ſhould keep as far as we may, from the Confines of that Fire that is apt to put our Paſſions into a Fever, and raiſe Diſorders in our Souls. The <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarites,</hi> who by the Law of God were obliged to abſtain from Wine, or ſtrong Drink, or any Liquor of Grapes, were forbidden alſo to eat of the Grape green or dried; they were not ſo much as to taſte of the Husk or Kernel, or of the Skin of a Grape, or Raiſin <note n="*" place="bottom">Numb. 6.3, 4.</note>.</p>
            <p>IF we know that ſuch or ſuch things have been Snares to us here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, and are like to prove ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; that ſuch a Game, or ſuch a
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:45005:46"/>Converſation, is like to be prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial to me in particular, and draw me to ſin; I am acceſſory to the Temptation, and to all the Sin and Miſchief that follows, if yet I will venture.</p>
            <p>THEY who ſeem the beſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, and reſolved, do yet need this Caution: For none can tell what they are, till Trial, and Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion diſcover them. To be Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, when a Man hath not where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withal to be otherwiſe: To be Chaſte, and have no Temptation to Uncleanneſs; to appear Meek, and have no Provocation; or for a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to be Juſt, and not to pilfer and ſteal, while his Maſter's Eye is upon him; this is comparatively a ſmall Matter. But to be chaſte in <hi>Sodom,</hi> to be temperate, as <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> in <hi>Aſia,</hi> amongſt the luxurious <hi>Epheſians;</hi> to be awed by the Fear of God, and kept from Folly, when ſolicited to it, as <hi>Joſeph;</hi> this is the Trial of our Strength. If a
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:45005:47"/>Man be ſo fooliſh, as out of choice to ſtand near a Precipice, a ſmall Puſh will throw him over, when a far greater would not have hurt him upon a Level.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STIN</hi> relates the Story of his Friend <hi>Alyppius,</hi> who, by the Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of his Acquaintance, conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to go to the Theatre; yet with a Reſolution not to open his Eyes, leſt the ſight of thoſe Spectacles ſhould intice his Heart: But being there, the Noiſe and ſudden ſhouting of the Multitude prevailed ſo far with him that he forgot his Reſolution, takes the liberty to ſee what occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned the Shout; and once ſeeing, is now ſo enflamed with Delight, that he ſhouts as the reſt do, and becomes a Frequenter of the Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre as others: All his Reſolution did not avail, when the Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was brought to his Senſe.</p>
            <p>IT is a bold and dangerous Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, to court the <hi>Opportunities</hi> of ſinning, to invite an Enemy, to
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:45005:47"/>imbrace a Danger; tho a Man do it, as he pretends, to get the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of a Victory, and to give Proof of his Piety in reſiſting; it is twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to one but he is ſurprized, and overcome: Like the Folly, as one obſerves, of that <hi>Egyptian</hi> who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged <hi>Fire</hi> for his <hi>God;</hi> and one day doing his Devotions, kiſſed his God after the manner of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers, and burnt his Lips. Juſt ſuch a Fool is he who hugs a Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, tho with a deſign of Vertue; he burns himſelf in the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood of the Flame, and is like to periſh in his own Folly. It is to call the Danger nearer, that we may run from it. And let Men mean never ſo well, they cannot act wiſely, who will go to meet the World, and invite the Devil, and venture upon his Ground: They conſider not, that by running upon Temptation, they have no Promiſe of God to be delivered out of it; and becauſe they <hi>Tempt</hi> him, he
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:45005:48"/>juſtly leaves them to miſcarry, as the Puniſhment of their Raſhneſs.</p>
            <p>BEWARE therefore of trying Concluſions, how near you may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to Sin, and not be defiled; how you adventure to gratify your Curioſity, to go where you may be enſnared, where your <hi>Danger</hi> is greater than your <hi>Buſineſs.</hi> You conſider not, that to be near Sin, is to be near the Wrath of God, and the Fire of Hell; and to come near it, is the common way of coming to it. It is the Devil's cunning to make you confident of your own Strength, to tell you you need not fear; you can run a greater Hazard than this, you can bear a ſtronger Temptation than this; What tho you are in bad Company, are you ſuch a Child that you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not govern your ſelf? But ſince our Fleſh and corrupt Inclination is on the Tempter's ſide, our ſtrongeſt Reſolutions may then fail us: And if we make bold with the Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:45005:48"/>and Occaſions of Sin, we Tempt God, and provoke him to leave us to our ſelves.</p>
            <p n="3">3. WHEN we run upon any ſuch thing as requires the Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Aſſiſtance of God's Grace and Spirit, without any Ground or Promiſe from the Word of God to expect it: When a Man of weak Shoulders will attempt to bear a Burden, that would require a <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>'s Back. When we will ruſh upon ſuch things, as are beyond our Ability and Strength, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect Extraordinary Help, without a Promiſe. As when, by the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of the ordinary way of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving our Minds in Knowledg, we think to do thoſe things unto which the greateſt Improvements of Knowledg are required. If the Sons of <hi>Sceva</hi> will undertake to exerciſe the Devil, no wonder if he prevail againſt them, <hi>Acts</hi> 19.16.</p>
            <p>THE Popiſh Vows of <hi>perpetual Virginity</hi> are a Tempting of God
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:45005:49"/>and Chriſt in this reſpect; becauſe there is <hi>no Promiſe</hi> of God's Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, that they ſhall be able to perform ſuch a Vow: There is no Promiſe, that whoever will reſolve and endeavour it, ſhall be able to lead a ſingle Life without <hi>Marriage.</hi> So the Apoſtles were offended with them that would injoin Chriſtians to obſerve the Jewiſh Ceremonies, after Chriſt's Aſcenſion to Heaven: Not only becauſe they were laid aſide by the Death of Chriſt, but becauſe there was <hi>no Promiſe</hi> of the Divine Preſence, and Aſſiſtance any longer in that Worſhip: This there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is called <hi>a Tempting of God,</hi> Acts 15.10.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="section">
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:45005:49"/>
            <head>SECT. XIII. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of Tempting God and Chriſt, as to his</hi> Patience.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly.</hi> WE Tempt him as to <hi>his Patience</hi> and <hi>Long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering.</hi> And thus the Jews are ſaid to tempt God, while they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled againſt him, and abuſed his Forbearance. What is termed <hi>the Day of Temptation</hi> in one place, is called <hi>the Day of Provocation</hi> in another. <hi>You have now tempted me,</hi> ſays God, <hi>theſe ten times, and will not obſerve my Orders, or hearken to my Voice;</hi> your continued Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience is a conſtant Tempting of me.</p>
            <p>TO how many of us may God ſay the like and worſe! You have tempted me, not only theſe ten
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:45005:50"/>times, but theſe <hi>ten</hi> Years, or <hi>twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> Years, or more; and would not obey my Voice, notwithſtanding many Convictions of Conſcience, many inſtructive Warnings and Reproofs, many loud Calls of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, and many Motions of my Spirit ſtriving with your Hearts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> You have tempted my Patience, and Long-ſuffering, and made a bold Trial how long I would bear with you.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="section">
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:45005:50"/>
            <head>SECT. XIV.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> 
                  <hi>The Improvement of this Diſcourſe for Conviction of Sin, and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation. The Aggravations of this Tempting Chriſt. The Danger of it, as applied to the Nation, from this Example of the Jews.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt.</hi> THIS may be improved for our <hi>Humiliation,</hi> with reference to the many Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, wherein we have been guilty of Tempting Chriſt. Upon a Review of the forementioned Particulars, how often may we juſtly charge our ſelves with this Sin! To affect us with it the more, I might repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the Evil of this Sin, partly from the Spring and Root of it, which is <hi>Infidelity,</hi> Unbelief, or Diſtruſt of God. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.18, 22, 23.
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:45005:51"/>
               <hi>They believed not God.</hi> Partly from the <hi>Diſobedience,</hi> and Rebellion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Divine Orders, with which it is attended. <hi>They Tempted God, and provoked the Moſt High,</hi> i. e. they rebelled againſt him.</p>
            <p>PARTLY from that Ingratitude, and Forgetfulneſs of God which this Sin implies, and from the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolence</hi> and <hi>Arrogance</hi> that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in ſuch a Trial of the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, Power and Goodneſs of God. For a Servant, or a Scholar, or any Inferior to try Experiments con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Honeſty, or the Skill of his Superiour, is a provoking piece of Inſolence. But this is nothing to the ſawcy Boldneſs of Rebellious Sinners againſt the Lord, and againſt his Chriſt. I might argue it like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe from its Likeneſs and Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to the Sin of the Devil; It is a horrid Imitation of the Devil's Crime, who is the Tempter.</p>
            <p>I MIGHT prove it alſo from the Severity of its Puniſhment, by
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:45005:51"/>Scripture-Examples and Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Theſe <hi>Jews</hi> are an eminent Inſtance, we read of Multitudes of them deſtroyed ſuddenly, <hi>The Wrath of God came upon them, while the Meat was in their Mouths.</hi> And, for another Inſtance of the like Guilt, they were deſtroyed by <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents:</hi> And afterwards, for conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing to tempt God, they were excluded the promiſed Land; they were refuſed Entrance into <hi>Canaan,</hi> and All of that Generation, except <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Joſhua,</hi> died in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs.</p>
            <p>THIS Inſtance ſhould be very Inſtructive and Monitory unto us, to take heed of Tempting God, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did. We reſemble them both in our Mercies, and in our Sins. God hath moſt eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly favour'd this Nation, and we have moſt highly provoked God.</p>
            <p>GREAT Things indeed he did for <hi>Iſrael:</hi> He meant (ſaith Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi>) to make that Nation a <hi>Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:45005:52"/>of Mercy. Heaven and Earth conſpir'd to bleſs them. Should I ſpeak of the Wonders of <hi>Egypt,</hi> I know not whether their Preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in it, or Deliverance out of it were the more Miraculous. Did they want a Guide? God himſelf goes before them in Fire. Did they want a Shelter? his Cloud is ſpread over them for a Covering. Did they want a Way? the Sea it ſelf ſhall make it, and be at once a Street and a Wall to them. Did they want Bread? Heaven it ſelf ſhall pour down the Food of Angels. Did they want Meat to their Bread? the Wind ſhall bring them whole Drifts of Quails into their Tents. Do they want Drink to both? the very Rocks ſhall yield it. Do they want Sutes of Apparel in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs? their Clothes ſhall not wax old on their Backs. Do they want Advice? God himſelf ſhall give his Vocal Oracle between the Cherubims. Do they want a Law?
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:45005:52"/>he ſhall come down upon <hi>Sinai,</hi> and deliver it in Fire, Thundring, Smoke, Earthquakes, and write it with his own Finger in Tables of Stone. Do they want Habitations? God ſhall provide them a Land that flows with Milk and Honey. Are they perſecuted? God ſtands in Fire between them and their Harms. Are they ſtung to Death? the Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen Serpent ſhall cure them. Are they reſiſted? The Walls of <hi>Jericho</hi> ſhall fall down alone: Hail-ſtones brain their Enemies: The Sun ſtood ſtill, to ſee <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s Revenge and Victory. O Great and Mighty Things that God did for <hi>Iſrael!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND if any Nation under Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven could either parallel or ſecond <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Favours of God, this poor little <hi>Iſland</hi> of ours is it. The Cloud of his Protection hath co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered us. The bloody Sea of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution hath given way to us, and we have paſſed it dry-ſhod. The true <hi>Manna</hi> from Heaven is rain'd
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:45005:53"/>down abundantly about our Tents. The Waters of Life ſpring forth plenteouſly among us. The bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Law of the Goſpel is given us from Heaven by the Hands of his Son, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BUT under all theſe and the like Obligations they Tempted God, and provoked the moſt High. Let us take heed of imitating their Sin, and Tempting God as they did, by not underſtanding his Wonders, by forgetting all his Works, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing to provoke him after ſuch National Deliverances as he has wrought for us. Are we not under the like Guilt on this Account? How ſlowly doth any thing that may be called <hi>Reformation</hi> go on? tho there be the Countenance of Magiſtracy to encourage it. What Inſtance of Pride and Luxury is abated? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If therefore after all God hath done, we thus continue to Tempt him by our <hi>Impenitence;</hi> it is poſſible, and more than poſſible, that we
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:45005:53"/>may yet be deſtroyed. Read <hi>Gen.</hi> 14. compared with the 18th Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and you find that <hi>Sodom,</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> and the Cities of the Plain, notwithſtanding the Victory and Succeſs which God had given them againſt their Enemies, by the Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Servants; yet for their Pride, and Idleneſs, and Uncleanneſs, and the abuſe of their Plenty and Peace, he ſoon after de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed them <hi>with Fire from Heaven,</hi> as a Warning to future Generations, and hath left it on Record for our Admonition.</p>
            <p>BUT <hi>the Jews</hi> are our moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable <hi>Example</hi> and <hi>Pattern.</hi> How miraculouſly did God deliver them out of <hi>Egypt!</hi> and yet how ſoon after were they brought to their Wits end at the Red Sea! God <hi>there</hi> appears for them, and makes bare his Arm for their Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the Overthrow of the Enemies; but that extraordinary Deliverance at <hi>the Red Sea</hi> did but
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:45005:54"/>enter them into the <hi>Wilderneſs;</hi> they were not preſently upon this, as they imagined, to take Poſſeſſion of the promiſed Land; God would try them in the Wilderneſs. There they murmured, and <hi>tempted God in the Deſart,</hi> and ever and anon he plagued them with one Inſtance of his Severity after another. He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered them often, but they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled again, and he is forced to puniſh them again: Inſomuch that when they were upon the very Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the promiſed Land, when they could look into <hi>Canaan,</hi> and needed only to go over and take Poſſeſſion, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.8, 9. yet, like a Ship in ſight of the Harbour, their Provocations againſt God raiſe a new Storm, and they are driven back again to Sea, and all the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers are drowned. <hi>God ſware in his Wrath, that none of them ſhould enter into his Reſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WE have reaſon to apprehend, that after all that God has done for us,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:45005:54"/>if yet we continue to tempt him, he may refuſe to ſtrengthen that which he has wrought for us; the faireſt Hopes of NATIONAL Eſtabliſhment may be blaſted, the neareſt Proſpect of compleat Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may be diſappointed; God may ſtop the Progreſs of the Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance he has given, and leave us to periſh by one another, or as a Prey to the Common Enemy. And who can tell but this may be the laſt Trial that He will ever make of this Generation? The Seaſon ſeems to be very Critical, Judgment and Mercy are ſtriving which ſhall get the better. But if yet we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel againſt him, deſpiſe his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, diſobey his Orders, blaſpheme the Son of God, and reject the everlaſting Goſpel, and will not know the things that belong unto our common Peace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If neither his late aſtoniſhing Kindneſs to us, nor the Apprehenſions of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved Diſpleaſure for miſimproving
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:45005:55"/>it, will make us ceaſe to Tempt him; but we ſtill harden our Hearts, as the <hi>Jews</hi> did; we have Reaſon to look for Wonders of Severity, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to thoſe of Mercy we have formerly had. We may Fear and Expect this as to <hi>the NATION;</hi> but however God may deal with that, yet as to particular Perſons, who continue to tempt God, <hi>there remains nothing</hi> for them <hi>but a fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful looking for of Judgment, and of fiery Indignation.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="section">
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:45005:55"/>
            <head>SECT. XV. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>An Exhortation to all ſorts of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, inſtead of Tempting Chriſt, to make Trial and Proof of his Goodneſs and Faithfulneſs, in a way of Duty, Obedience, and Dependance.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly.</hi> LET us then, inſtead of Tempting Chriſt as we have done, reſolve for the future to make that <hi>Trial</hi> and <hi>Proof</hi> of him, which he allows and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires us to do. We read ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in Scripture how God conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended to the Weakneſs of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and gave them leave to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand <hi>a Sign</hi> of him, upon ſuch and ſuch Particular Occaſions. <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deon</hi> had an expreſs Order for his <hi>Sign, Judg.</hi> 7. And <hi>Ahaz</hi> had leave
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:45005:56"/>to ask <hi>one,</hi> for the increaſe of his Faith; and it ſeems as if he did not do well to refuſe it, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 7.12. But ſometimes, without an expreſs Command, holy Men have asked of God <hi>a Sign;</hi> as <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 15. <hi>Whereby ſhall I know, that I ſhall inherit the Land of</hi> Canaan? So <hi>Eliezer, Abraham</hi>'s Servant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.14. So <hi>Jonathan,</hi> 1 Sam. 14.10. In theſe and other extraordinary Caſes, what there was of Propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Inſtinct, or Inſpiration to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant them, we know not; and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they did well or ill in demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Sign of God, we can hardly ſay: But our Caſe is plain, where we have the Warrant of Divine <hi>Precept,</hi> and a <hi>Promiſe</hi> alſo for our Incouragement.</p>
            <p>LET us then make Trial of the Faithfulneſs, and the Goodneſs of God, in the ways of Obedience. <hi>Prove me now,</hi> ſays God, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Do any of you kindle a Fire upon mine Altar for nought?</hi> Do you offer a
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:45005:56"/>Sacrifice to me without profiting your ſelves? <hi>Tho you have robbed me, ſaith the Lord, as to Tithes and Offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, even this whole Nation.</hi> Chap. 3. v. 9, 10. <hi>Yet bring them into the Store-houſe, that there may be Meat in my Houſe; and prove me now here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts; ſee if I will not open unto you the Windows of Heaven, and pour you out an abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant Bleſſing, that you ſhall not have room to receive it; and make that all Nations ſhall call you bleſſed.</hi> To the like purpoſe we read in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.13, 14. <hi>O that my People had hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened unto me, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>had walked in my Ways! I ſhould ſoon have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued their Enemies, and turned my Hand againſt their Adverſaries.</hi> But they would not try me, and truſt me.</p>
            <p>GOD condeſcends to ſpeak ſuch Language unto All of us. <hi>Prove me,</hi> ſaith he, by obeying my Voice, and hearkening to my Word: En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into my Service, ſee whether
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:45005:57"/>I am a hard Maſter: Take my Yoke upon you, ſee whether it be not eaſy, and my Burden light: Try whether my Service be not bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than that of Sin, and the World: See whether any can do for you, that which I can, and will do. Come unto me, <hi>ſays Chriſt,</hi> if you are <hi>weary</hi> and <hi>heavy laden,</hi> and ſee whether I cannot give you <hi>Reſt.</hi> Do but make <hi>a Trial,</hi> whether the Ways of Wiſdom be not Pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and her Paths Peace. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn not Religion for a melancholy, tedious, burdenſome thing, before you have found it ſo upon <hi>Trial.</hi> See whether ſeeking the Kingdom of God, and the Righteouſneſs thereof, in <hi>the firſt place,</hi> be not the way, to have all other things added, in the beſt Proportion. Make a Trial, at leaſt for a time, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to walk uprightly, and keep a Conſcience void of Offence towards God and Man, be not the only way to walk ſurely in the moſt difficult
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:45005:57"/>Times, and turn of Affairs, publick or private.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>PROVE me now,</hi> ſays God, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he that fears God and works Righteouſneſs ſhall not be Accepted. See whether I am a barren Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or a Land of Drought; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ever you ſhall have reaſon to Repent your turning from Sin and Vanity, to walk in my Way; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ever any ſhall be Loſers by their Fidelity to me.</p>
            <p>O THAT Magiſtrates, Miniſters, Gentlemen, Students, Merchants, Tradeſmen, Parents, Children, Heads of Families, and Servants, younger, elder Perſons, under what Denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation ſoever they may be ranked, would <hi>All</hi> in their ſeveral places, inſtead of Tempting Chriſt, make a Trial of his Faithfulneſs to his Promiſes, unto ſuch as are diligent, and faithful to the performance of the Duty! O that <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> would but try, whether Fidelity to God, and Zeal for his Glory, and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:45005:58"/>Concern for his Honour, and Care that his Laws be obſerved, and the Violation of them puniſhed; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this be not the beſt way to their own Safety, Honour and Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment, and the only Exaltation and Security of the People! O that <hi>Miniſters</hi> would but try, whether hearty Love to God and Chriſt, and the Souls of Men, and fervent De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and Endeavours to approve our ſelves to the All-ſeeing God, in ſeeking to promote the Faith, and Holineſs, and Joy of Chriſtians, and their Union, Love and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord one with another, be not the beſt way for our Acceptance and Succeſs!</p>
            <p>O that <hi>Merchants,</hi> and <hi>Tradeſmen</hi> would but try, by conſtant Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon God, and daily Prayer in their Cloſets and Families, and ſtrict Juſtice and Righteouſneſs in their Dealings, and by chuſing and encouraging ſuch Servants as fear the Lord, and by keeping up the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:45005:58"/>Worſhip and Authority of God in their Houſes; whether this be not the beſt way to baniſh the Curſe of God from their Habitation, and to obtain that Bleſſing of Heaven up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Diligence in their Callings, which will make Rich, without the Addition of Sorrow!</p>
            <p>O that <hi>Parents</hi> would try, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by dedicating their Children to God betimes, and educating them diligently in the Fear and Nurture of the Lord, and diſgracing Sin to them, telling them the Evil and the Danger of it, and antidoting them againſt Temptation, ſaving them from Pride, and Idleneſs, and evil Company, making Religion plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to them, and ſetting an holy Example before them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>this</hi> be not the beſt, and only way to have Comfort in them!</p>
            <p>O that we, who are <hi>the Children of Religious, Holy Parents,</hi> would but try whether there will not be a double Bleſſing from Heaven upon
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:45005:59"/>us, if we own <hi>our Fathers God,</hi> and <hi>our Mothers God:</hi> If we keep within the Bond of his Covenant, and remember his Commandments to do them; if we cut not off the Entail of Covenant-Bleſſings with our own Hands; if we obey the God of our Fathers, with a perfect and upright Heart! Let us <hi>prove him,</hi> and try whether he will not fulfil his Promiſe, That <hi>the Mercy of the Lord ſhall be from everlaſting to everlaſting to them that fear him, and his Righteouſneſs (or Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) to the Childrens Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN SHORT, let us All reſolve to Tempt God and Chriſt no more, as we have done, but to prove him by our holy Obedience. And we ſhall find by Experience, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting our Way to God in well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing, is the wiſeſt, and eaſieſt, and ſweeteſt Life, through all the Changes of this preſent World: That by caſting our Bread upon the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:45005:59"/>Waters, and giving to the Poor, we do but lend unto the Lord, and he will ſurely repay it: That to ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy the Lord's-Day, is the proper Method to have the Bleſſing of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven all the Week: That to live the Life of the Righteous, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to remember and ſerve him in our Youth, is the only proper Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod for a long Life, and a good old Age, or a peaceful Death, a Comfortable Account, and a Bleſſed Eternity.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:45005:60"/>
            <list>
               <head>Theſe following Books are publiſhed by Mr. <hi>John Shower,</hi> and ſold by <hi>John Lawrence</hi> at the Angel in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>SOme Account of the Holy <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> of Mr. <hi>Henry Gearing,</hi> late Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen of <hi>London:</hi> Who departed this Life <hi>January</hi> the 4th, 169¾ Aged 61. With the <hi>Trial</hi> and <hi>Character</hi> of a <hi>Real Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> collected out of his Papers, for the Examination of himſelf: From which ſeveral other Particulars are added, for the <hi>Inſtruction, Encouragement,</hi> and <hi>Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> of Chriſtians.</item>
               <item>The Mourners Companion; or Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Diſcourſes from ſeveral Texts, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Price bound 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Death a Deliverance: A Funeral Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, to bind up with the Mourners Companion.</item>
               <item>Sacramental Diſcourſes on ſeveral Texts, before and after the Lord's-Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, together with a Paraphraſe on the Lord's-Prayer, 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Price bound 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:45005:60"/>
               <item>Practical Reflections on the late Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes in <hi>Jamaica, Engalnd, Sicily, Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> &amp;c. with a particular Hiſtorical Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of thoſe, and divers other Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes. Price bound 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Day of Grace: Or a Diſcourſe concerning the Poſſibility, and Fear of its being paſt before Death: Shewing the groundleſs Doubts, and miſtaken Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of ſome, as to their being fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally forſaken and left of God; with the dangerous Symptoms and Approaches of others to ſuch a ſad State: In four Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons from <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.11, 12. in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>Serious Reflections on Time and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, with ſome other Subjects, Moral and Divine: To which is annexed an Appendix, concerning the firſt Day of the Year; how obſerved by the Jews, and may beſt be employed by a ſerious Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. <hi>The Third Edition,</hi> 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>In the Preſs of the ſame Author<hi>'s.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>A Diſcourſe of Family Religion, in three Letters to a Friend, in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:45005:61"/>
               <head>BOOK'S Printed for <hi>John Lawrence,</hi> at the Angel in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>MR. <hi>Slater</hi>'s Sermon on the Funeral of Mr. <hi>John Reynolds</hi> Miniſter. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>—His Sermon on the Funeral of Mr. <hi>Fricher.</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>—His Sermon on the Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving-Day, <hi>Octob.</hi> 27, 1692. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Giles Firmin</hi>'s Anſwer to <hi>R. Davis,</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>An Apology for the Miniſters who ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> his Book, ſhewing that the Goſpel which they preach, is the old everlaſting Goſpel of Chriſt: Againſt the <hi>Antinomians.</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Hammond</hi>'s Sermon on Mr. <hi>Steel</hi>'s Funeral. 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Miſcellanea Sacra:</hi> Containing Scriptural Meditations, Divine Breathings, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſional Reflections, and ſacred Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ems. 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>A perpetual Almanack of Spiritual Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations. 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>The Triumphs of Grace, in the laſt Words and edifying Death of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Margaret de la Muſſe.</hi> 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Aickin</hi>'s Engliſh Grammar; or the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Tongue reduced to Grammatical Rules. 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clavis Grammatica,</hi> or a ready way to the Latin Tongue. 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The is now in the Preſs,</head>
               <item>A Diſcourſe of Family Religion by the Reverend Mr. <hi>Samuel Slater,</hi> in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Printed for <hi>J. Lawrence.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:45005:61"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
